<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<dataset><item><text>An abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) is a swelling in the aorta, the artery that carries blood from the heart to the tummy (abdomen). Most aneurysms do not cause any problems, but they can be serious because there's a risk they could burst (rupture). Symptoms of abdominal aortic aneurysm Abdominal aortic aneurysm often has no symptoms. You usually only find out you have one during an abdominal aortic aneurysm screening test or during tests for another condition. If an aneurysm gets bigger, you might sometimes notice: tummy or back pain a pulsing feeling in your tummy Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you have tummy or back pain that does not go away or keeps coming back you feel a lump in your tummy These symptoms can be caused by lots of things and do not mean you have an abdominal aortic aneurysm, but it's best to get them checked. Immediate action required: Call 999 if you or someone else: have sudden, severe pain in your tummy or back are struggling to breathe or have stopped breathing have pale or grey skin (on brown or black skin this may be easier to see on the palms of the hands or soles of the feet) lose consciousness These could be signs of an abdominal aortic aneurysm bursting (rupturing). This is a life-threatening emergency that needs to be treated in hospital as soon as possible. Tests for abdominal aortic aneurysm The main test to find out if you have an abdominal aortic aneurysm is an ultrasound scan of your tummy. A small device is placed on your tummy and images of the inside of your tummy will be shown on a screen. You'll usually be told if you have an aneurysm at the end of the test. You’ll also be told how big it is: small (3cm to 4.4cm or smaller) medium (4.5cm to 5.4cm) large (5.5cm or bigger) Screening for abdominal aortic aneurysm An ultrasound test is offered to all men when they turn 65, as they're most at risk of getting an abdominal aortic aneurysm. This is called abdominal aortic aneurysm screening . Treatment for abdominal aortic aneurysm Treatment for an abdominal aortic aneurysm usually depends on how big it is and if you have symptoms. If it's small, lifestyle changes such as quitting smoking and eating healthily may be recommended to help stop it getting bigger. Sometimes you may need: medicines to lower your blood pressure and cholesterol level, which may help stop the aneurysm getting bigger surgery to reduce the risk of the aneurysm bursting - this may be done if your AAA is large (5.5cm or bigger), is quickly getting bigger or is painful Surgery has risks and side effects which your doctor or surgeon should discuss with you. Abdominal aortic aneurysms often get bigger over time. You'll usually need regular scans to see if it's getting bigger. If your aneurysm ruptures, you’ll need emergency surgery to treat it. How to lower your risk of getting an abdominal aortic aneurysm Making healthy lifestyle changes can help lower your risk of getting an abdominal aortic aneurysm, or stop one from getting bigger. Do eat healthily exercise regularly try to lose weight if you're overweight try to cut down on alcohol Don’t do not smoke Information: Find out how to get help to quit smoking Causes of an abdominal aortic aneurysm An abdominal aortic aneurysm happens when the main artery that carries blood from the heart to the tummy (the aorta) becomes weakened. It's not always clear what causes it, but some people have a higher chance of getting one. You’re more at risk if you: are male and aged 65 or over smoke or used to smoke have high blood pressure have high cholesterol have a close relative who's had an abdominal aortic aneurysm have coronary or peripheral artery disease ( atherosclerosis ) have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) have a condition such as Marfan syndrome Sometimes an abdominal aortic aneurysm can be caused by an infection, but this is rare. Video: Abdominal aortic aneurysm This video shows what an abdominal aortic aneurysm looks like. Media last reviewed: 10 October 2024 Media review due: 10 October 2027 Page last reviewed: 14 June 2023 Next review due: 14 June 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of acanthosis nigricans The main symptom of acanthosis nigricans is patches of skin that are darker and thicker than usual. They can appear anywhere on the body. The patches are dry and feel similar to velvet. Credit: Benedicte Desrus / Alamy Stock Photo They're most common in skin folds, such as the armpits, neck or groin. Credit: CID, ISM /SCIENCE PHOTO LIBRARY Some people also have tiny growths (skin tags) on the patches. Credit: ANDRE LABBE, ISM/SCIENCE PHOTO LIBRARY The patches often appear gradually without any other symptoms. Sometimes the skin may be itchy. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you have new dark patches on your skin you have any skin changes you're unsure about What happens at your appointment A GP can usually tell if it's acanthosis nigricans by looking at your skin. Although acanthosis nigricans is usually harmless, it's best to get any skin changes checked out. Rarely, it can be a sign of something more serious, such as cancer. You may need some tests to find out what's causing the patches. Causes of acanthosis nigricans The most common cause of acanthosis nigricans is obesity . Other causes include: type 2 diabetes conditions that affect hormone levels – such as Cushing's syndrome , polycystic ovary syndrome or an underactive thyroid taking certain medicines – including steroids or hormone treatments like the contraceptive pill rarely, cancer – usually stomach cancer rarely, a faulty gene inherited from your parents Sometimes healthy people with no other conditions get acanthosis nigricans. This is more common in people with black or brown skin. Treating acanthosis nigricans Once a GP knows what's causing acanthosis nigricans, they can recommend the best treatment. The patches should fade over time once the cause is treated. If you're very overweight, a GP may recommend losing weight. Depending on the cause, they may also recommend: medicine to balance your hormones medicine to balance your insulin levels changing your medicine to one that does not cause the patches There's no specific treatment for the patches themselves. A skin specialist (dermatologist) may be able to suggest treatments to improve their appearance, but finding and treating the cause is usually recommended first. Page last reviewed: 04 July 2024 Next review due: 04 July 2027</text><label>5</label></item><item><text>Achalasia is a rare disorder of the food pipe (oesophagus), which can make it difficult to swallow food and drink. Normally, the muscles of the oesophagus contract to squeeze food along towards the stomach. A ring of muscle at the end of the food pipe then relaxes to let food into the stomach. In achalasia, the muscles in the oesophagus do not contract correctly and the ring of muscle can fail to open properly, or does not open at all. Food and drink cannot pass into the stomach and becomes stuck. It is often brought back up. Symptoms of achalasia Not everyone with achalasia will have symptoms. But most people with achalasia will find it difficult to swallow food or drink (known as dysphagia ). Swallowing tends to get gradually more difficult or painful over a couple of years, to the point where it is sometimes impossible. Other symptoms include: bringing back up undigested food choking and coughing fits heartburn chest pain repeated chest infections drooling of vomit or saliva gradual but significant weight loss Symptoms of achalasia may start at any time of life. Swallowing problems can also be caused by cancers of the mouth, throat and oesophagus. There’s a link between long-term achalasia and the risk of developing cancer of the oesophagus , but the risk is small. It’s always important to get symptoms checked straight away, even if your symptoms are not bothering you. Causes of achalasia Achalasia is thought to happen when the nerves in the oesophagus become damaged and stop working properly, which is why the muscles and ring of muscle do not work. The exact cause of this is unknown. In some people, it may be linked to a viral infection. It may also be associated with having an autoimmune condition, where the body's immune system attacks healthy cells, tissue and organs. In rare cases, it's possible that achalasia is caused by a faulty gene. Diagnosing achalasia If a GP thinks you have achalasia, you'll be referred to hospital to have some diagnostic tests. Achalasia may also be diagnosed during an investigation, such as a chest X-ray , for another reason. The tests for achalasia include: manometry – a small plastic tube is passed through your mouth or nose into your oesophagus to measure the muscle pressure along it at different points. barium swallow – you drink a white liquid containing the chemical barium and X-rays are taken. The barium shows up clearly on X-ray so the doctor can see how long it takes to move into your stomach. endoscopy – a thin, flexible instrument called an endoscope is passed down your throat to allow the doctor to look directly at the lining of your oesophagus, the ring of muscle and your stomach. Treatments for achalasia There is no cure for achalasia, but treatment can help relieve the symptoms and make swallowing easier. Your doctors will talk to you about the risks and benefits of the different treatment options. Medicine Medicines, such as nitrates or nifedipine , can help to relax the muscles in your oesophagus. This makes swallowing easier and less painful for some people, although they do not work for everyone. The effect only lasts for a short time, so medicine may be used to ease symptoms while you wait for a more permanent treatment. They may cause headaches, but this usually improves over time. Stretching the muscle (balloon dilation) Under a sedative, or sometimes a general anaesthetic , a balloon is passed into the oesophagus using a long, thin flexible tube ( endoscope ). The balloon is then inflated to help stretch the ring of muscle that lets food into your stomach. This improves swallowing for most people, but you may need treatment several times before your symptoms improve. Balloon dilatation does carry a small risk of tearing the oesophagus (oesophageal rupture), which may require emergency surgery. Botox injection Using an endoscope, botox is injected into the ring of muscle that lets food into your stomach, causing it to relax. It is usually effective for a few months and occasionally for a few years, but it has to be repeated. This is usually painless, and can be used for temporary relief in people who are not able to have other treatments. Surgery Under general anaesthetic, the muscle fibres in the ring of muscle that lets food into your stomach are cut. This is done using keyhole surgery ( laparoscopy ) and is called Heller's myotomy. It can permanently make swallowing easier. Often a second procedure will be done at the same time to stop you getting acid reflux and heartburn , which can be a side effect of the Heller's myotomy operation. Your surgeon will talk to you about this and any other surgical options which may be the best option for you. Follow-up treatment Balloon dilation and surgery can both cause side effects such as acid reflux and heartburn and chest pain. A GP may be able to prescribe medicine to help with this, and your surgeon may suggest you take this medicine routinely. It's normal for chest pain to persist for a while after treatment. You should see a GP if you still have swallowing difficulties or are continuing to lose weight after treatment. Information: Read about living with achalasia on the Achalasia Action website Page last reviewed: 05 December 2023 Next review due: 05 December 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of reflux in babies Reflux usually starts before a baby is 8 weeks old and gets better by the time they're 1. Symptoms of reflux in babies include: bringing up milk or being sick during or shortly after feeding coughing or hiccupping when feeding being unsettled during feeding swallowing or gulping after burping or feeding crying and not settling not gaining weight as they're not keeping enough food down Sometimes babies may have signs of reflux but will not bring up milk or be sick. This is known as silent reflux. Things you can try to ease reflux in babies It's common for a baby under the age of 1 to bring up a little bit of milk during or shortly after a feed, without being distressed. Your baby does not usually need to see a doctor if they have reflux, as long as they're happy, healthy and gaining weight. If symptoms of reflux seem to be bothering your baby, there are things you can do to help. Do ask a health visitor for advice and support get advice about your baby's breastfeeding position or how to bottle feed your baby hold your baby upright during feeding and for as long as possible after feeding burp your baby regularly during feeds make sure your baby sleeps flat on their back (they should not sleep on their side or front) Don’t do not raise the head of their cot or Moses basket Non-urgent advice: See a GP if your baby: is not improving after trying things to ease reflux gets reflux for the first time after they're 6 months old is older than 1 and still has reflux is not gaining weight or is losing weight Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or call NHS 111 if your baby: has vomit that's green or yellow, or has blood in it is projectile vomiting (being sick with more force than usual) has blood in their poo has a swollen or tender tummy has a very high temperature or they feel hot or shivery keeps being sick and cannot keep fluid down has diarrhoea that lasts for over a week or has signs of dehydration will not stop crying and is very distressed is refusing to feed Also call your GP or 111 if you have any other concerns about your baby. Treatment for reflux in babies A GP or specialist may want to check whether your baby has an allergy to cow's milk, because the symptoms can be very similar to reflux. If there's no sign of cow' milk allergy, they may recommend treatments for reflux. If your baby is formula-fed, they may recommend: a powder that's mixed with formula, to thicken it a pre-thickened formula milk If the thickening powder does not help or your baby is breastfed, a GP or specialist might recommend medicines that help with distress from reflux and stop their stomach from producing as much acid. Very rarely, surgery might be needed to strengthen the muscle that stops food or milk travelling back up. This is usually only after trying other things or if their reflux is severe. Causes of reflux Reflux usually happens because the ring of muscle inside your baby's food pipe (oesophagus) can be weak, which allows milk to come back up easily. This muscle will get stronger as your baby gets older and the reflux should stop. Page last reviewed: 10 June 2025 Next review due: 10 June 2028</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Heartburn is a burning feeling in the chest caused by stomach acid travelling up towards the throat (acid reflux). If it keeps happening, it may be called gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (GORD). Symptoms of acid reflux The main symptoms of acid reflux are: heartburn – a burning sensation in the middle of your chest an unpleasant sour taste in your mouth, caused by stomach acid You may also have: a cough or hiccups that keep coming back a hoarse voice bad breath bloating and feeling sick Symptoms are often worse after eating, when lying down and when bending over. Causes of heartburn and acid reflux Lots of people get heartburn from time to time. There's often no obvious reason why. Sometimes it's caused or made worse by: certain food and drink – such as coffee, tomatoes, alcohol, chocolate and fatty or spicy foods being overweight smoking pregnancy - find out more about indigestion and heartburn in pregnancy stress and anxiety an increase in some types of hormones, such as progesterone and oestrogen some medicines, such as anti-inflammatory painkillers (like ibuprofen ) a hiatus hernia – when part of your stomach moves up into your chest a stomach ulcer a bacterial infection in your stomach How you can ease heartburn and acid reflux yourself Simple lifestyle changes can help stop or reduce heartburn. Do eat smaller, more frequent meals try to lose weight if you're overweight try to find ways to relax Don’t do not have food or drink that triggers your symptoms do not eat within 3 or 4 hours before bed do not wear clothes that are tight around your waist do not smoke do not drink too much alcohol do not stop taking any prescribed medicine without speaking to a doctor first You may find that using wood, bricks or books to raise the head of your bed by around 10 to 20cm, so your chest and head are above your waist, helps relieve symptoms. This can help stop stomach acid travelling up towards your throat. But do not try to achieve the same effect by using additional pillows, as this can increase pressure on your belly and make your symptoms worse. A pharmacist can help with heartburn and acid reflux Speak to a pharmacist for advice if you keep getting heartburn. They may recommend medicines called antacids or alginates that can help ease your symptoms. It's best to take these with food or soon after eating, as this is when you're most likely to get heartburn. They may also work for longer if taken with food. Although antacids and alginates help symptoms in the short term, they will not cure the problem and should not be taken regularly for long periods. If you're pregnant, a pharmacist can advise you about medicines you can take. Find a pharmacy Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: lifestyle changes and pharmacy medicines are not helping your heartburn you have heartburn most days you also have other symptoms, like food getting stuck in your throat, frequently being sick, or losing weight for no reason A GP can provide alternative or stronger treatments and help rule out any more serious causes of your symptoms. If at any time you feel your symptoms are getting worse, contact a GP, go to 111.nhs.uk or call 111. Treatment for heartburn and acid reflux from a GP If you have acid reflux, a GP may prescribe a medicine called a proton pump inhibitor (PPI) that reduces how much acid your stomach makes. PPIs include: omeprazole lansoprazole You'll usually need to take this type of medicine for 4 or 8 weeks, depending on how serious your acid reflux is. Go back to the GP if your symptoms return after stopping your medicine. You may need a long-term prescription. Important If a PPI does not help, your doctor may suggest trying a different type of medicine called an H2 receptor antagonist, such as famotidine. Tests and treatments for severe heartburn and acid reflux If medicines do not help or your symptoms are severe, a GP may refer you to a specialist for: tests to find out what's causing your symptoms, such as a gastroscopy (where a thin tube with a camera inside it is passed down your throat and into your stomach) tests to check for bacteria that can cause heartburn – this can be treated with a combination of antibiotics and PPIs surgery on your stomach or food pipe (oesophagus) to stop acid reflux Page last reviewed: 20 November 2023 Next review due: 20 November 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>An acoustic neuroma is a type of non-cancerous (benign) brain tumour. It's also known as a vestibular schwannoma. A benign brain tumour is a growth in the brain that usually grows slowly over many years and does not spread to other parts of the body. Acoustic neuromas grow on the nerve used for hearing and balance, which can cause problems such as hearing loss and unsteadiness. They can sometimes be serious if they become very large, but most are picked up and treated before they reach this stage. Acoustic neuromas tend to affect adults aged 30 to 60 and usually have no obvious cause, although a small number of cases are the result of a genetic condition called neurofibromatosis type 2 (NF2) . Symptoms of an acoustic neuroma An acoustic neuroma may not cause any obvious symptoms at first. Any symptoms tend to develop gradually and often include: hearing loss that usually only affects 1 ear hearing sounds that come from inside the body ( tinnitus ) the sensation that you're moving or spinning ( vertigo ) A large acoustic neuroma can also sometimes cause: persistent headaches temporary blurred or double vision numbness, pain or weakness on 1 side of the face problems with limb co-ordination ( ataxia ) on 1 side of the body voice changes or difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) Getting medical advice See your GP if you have persistent or troublesome symptoms that you're worried could be caused by an acoustic neuroma. Acoustic neuromas can be difficult to diagnose because the symptoms can be caused by other conditions, such as Ménière's disease . If your GP thinks you could have an acoustic neuroma, you'll be referred to a hospital or clinic for further tests, such as: hearing tests to check for hearing problems and determine whether they're caused by a problem with your nerves an MRI scan , which uses strong magnetic fields and radio waves to produce a detailed picture of the inside of your head a CT scan , which uses a series of X-rays to create a detailed image of the inside of your head Treatments for acoustic neuromas There are several different treatment options for an acoustic neuroma, depending on the size and position of your tumour, how fast it's growing and your general health. The main options are: monitoring the tumour – small tumours often just need to be monitored with regular MRI scans, and treatment is generally only recommended if scans show it's getting bigger brain surgery – surgery to remove all or some of the tumour through a cut in the skull may be carried out under general anaesthetic if it's large or getting bigger stereotactic radiosurgery – small tumours, or any pieces of a larger tumour that remain after surgery, may be treated with a precise beam of radiation to stop them getting any bigger All these options carry some risks. For example, surgery and radiosurgery can sometimes cause facial numbness or an inability to move part of your face ( paralysis ). Speak to your specialist about the best option for you and what the benefits and risks are. Outlook for acoustic neuromas Large acoustic neuromas can be serious because they can sometimes cause a life-threatening build-up of fluid in the brain ( hydrocephalus ). But it's rare for them to reach this stage. Many grow very slowly or not at all, and those that grow more quickly can be treated before they become too big. Even with treatment, symptoms such as hearing loss and tinnitus can persist and affect your ability to work, communicate and drive. These problems may need additional treatment. Read more about treating hearing loss and treating tinnitus . An acoustic neuroma can occasionally return after treatment. This is thought to happen to around 1 in every 20 people who have had surgical removal. You'll probably continue having regular MRI scans after any treatment to check if the tumour is growing again or coming back. Page last reviewed: 29 November 2022 Next review due: 29 November 2025</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of acromegaly Symptoms of acromegaly can develop slowly. They may include: swollen hands and feet tiredness or difficulty sleeping sleep apnoea sweating numbness and weakness in your hands abnormal height growth in children and teenagers (gigantism) body growth – feet, fingers, head, tongue and neck may increase in size headaches joint pain thicker, more oily skin a deeper voice irregular periods erection problems You usually get acromegaly between the ages of 30 and 50 years old, but you can get symptoms at any age. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you think you may have acromegaly Early diagnosis and treatment can stop symptoms getting worse. Causes of acromegaly Acromegaly is usually caused by an adenoma (a non-cancerous tumour ) in the pituitary gland. This is a pea-sized gland at the back of your brain. An adenoma can cause you to produce too much growth hormone. Acromegaly is not usually passed on from your parents (inherited). What happens at your appointment Acromegaly may take time to be diagnosed. If the GP thinks you have it, they may ask to see photographs of you from the past couple of years to check any changes. They may also refer you to a specialist for tests, including: blood tests an MRI scan of your brain to see if you have a tumour Treatments for acromegaly Treatments for acromegaly can include: surgery to remove the tumour radiotherapy to target the tumour and reduce growth hormone levels injections or tablets to reduce growth hormone levels Treatment usually stops your body producing too much growth hormone and usually improves your symptoms. After treatment, you'll continue to have appointments with a specialist. They can monitor how well your pituitary gland is working and check that your treatment is right for you. Complications of acromegaly Acromegaly can increase your risk of: type 2 diabetes high blood pressure (hypertension) heart disease bowel polyps You'll have regular health checks to monitor these conditions, including colonoscopy screenings to check for bowel polyps. Recording information about you and your condition If you have acromegaly, your care team will pass information on to the National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service (NCARDRS) . This helps scientists find better ways to treat and prevent this condition. You can opt out of the register at any time. Information: Find out more The Pituitary Foundation Page last reviewed: 19 December 2024 Next review due: 19 December 2027</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Actinic keratoses (also called solar keratoses) are dry, scaly patches of skin that have been damaged by the sun. It's not usually serious, but there's a small chance the patches could become skin cancer. Protecting your skin in the sun and watching out for changes can help. Symptoms of actinic keratoses Actinic keratoses patches: can feel dry, rough and scaly, or like sandpaper are usually between 1cm and 2cm in size can be the same colour as your skin, or range from pink to red to brown may be itchy Credit: NAS Medical / Alamy Stock Photo The patches usually appear on areas of your body that are often exposed to the sun, such as your face, hands and arms, ears, scalp and legs. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you notice new patches on your skin the patches begin to bleed, get bigger, change colour, feel tender or develop into a lump a patch appears on your lips It's important to get these skin changes checked in case they're being caused by something more serious, such as skin cancer. Treatment for actinic keratoses If you only have 1 actinic keratoses patch, a GP might suggest waiting to see if it goes away by itself. If you have more than 1 patch, or a patch is causing you problems such as pain and itchiness, treatment is usually recommended. A GP may refer you to a skin specialist (dermatologist). Treatments for actinic keratoses include: prescription creams and gels freezing the patches (cryotherapy) – this makes the patches turn into blisters and fall off after a few weeks surgery to cut out or scrape away the patches – you'll be given a local anaesthetic first, so it does not hurt photodynamic therapy (PDT), where special cream is applied to the patches and a light is shone on them Things you can do if you have actinic keratoses There are things you can do to stop your actinic keratoses patches getting worse and lower your chances of developing skin cancer. Do check your skin regularly for any changes use sunscreen with a sun protection factor (SPF) of at least 30 before going out in the sun and reapply regularly wear a hat and clothing that fully covers your arms and legs when you're out in the sun Don’t do not sunbathe do not use sunlamps or sunbeds as these can also damage your skin do not go into the sun between 11am and 3pm – this is when the sun is at its strongest Information: Consider taking 10 micrograms of vitamin D a day if you always cover up outdoors. This is because you may not get enough vitamin D from sunlight. Page last reviewed: 14 June 2023 Next review due: 14 June 2026</text><label>5</label></item><item><text>Actinomycosis is a rare type of bacterial infection. It can be very serious but can usually be treated with antibiotics. How you get actinomycosis The bacteria that cause actinomycosis normally live harmlessly in the body. They only cause an infection if they get into the lining of areas such as the mouth or gut. You cannot spread the infection to other people. Any part of the body can be infected, but the head and neck, chest, tummy and pelvis are most commonly affected. Possible causes of actinomycosis include: tooth decay and mouth infections mouth injuries inhaling food or liquid intrauterine devices (IUDs) dental or tummy surgery radiotherapy You're more likely to get actinomycosis if you have type 2 diabetes or a weakened immune system. Symptoms of actinomycosis Symptoms of actinomycosis depend on what part of the body is affected. Actinomycosis symptoms in different areas of the body Area of the body Symptoms Jaw or mouth Lumps in your cheek or neck, difficulty chewing, pus leaking from your skin Lungs Shortness of breath, chest pain, a cough, pus leaking from the skin on your chest Tummy Diarrhoea or constipation, pain, a lump or swelling in your tummy, pus leaking from the skin on your tummy Pelvis Pain low down in your tummy, vaginal bleeding or unusual discharge, a lump or swelling in your lower tummy Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you have symptoms of actinomycosis Treatment for actinomycosis Actinomycosis is treated with antibiotics. Treatment starts off in hospital with antibiotics given directly into a vein (intravenously). When you're well enough to go home, you'll be given antibiotic tablets to take for a few months. It's important to keep taking antibiotics until they're finished, even when you feel better. You might also need surgery to drain areas of pus (abscesses) and remove the surrounding area of skin if it's infected. How to prevent actinomycosis Actinomycosis is very rare, so the chances of getting it are extremely small. You can help reduce your risk by looking after your teeth and gums . Page last reviewed: 25 July 2023 Next review due: 25 July 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Acute cholecystitis is inflammation of the gallbladder. It usually happens when a gallstone blocks the cystic duct. Gallstones are small stones, usually made of cholesterol, that form in the gallbladder. The cystic duct is the main opening of the gallbladder. Gallstones are very common, affecting more than 1 in 10 adults in the UK. They do not usually cause symptoms, but can occasionally cause episodes of pain (biliary colic) or acute cholecystitis. Acute cholecystitis is potentially serious because of the risk of complications. It usually needs to be treated in hospital with rest, intravenous fluids and antibiotics . Symptoms of acute cholecystitis The main symptom of acute cholecystitis is a sudden, sharp pain in the upper right-hand side of your tummy (abdomen). This pain spreads towards your right shoulder. The affected part of the tummy is usually very tender, and breathing deeply can make the pain worse. Unlike other types of abdominal pain , the pain of acute cholecystitis is usually persistent and does not go away within a few hours. Some people may have additional symptoms, such as: a high temperature feeling sick being sick sweating loss of appetite yellowing of the skin and the whites of the eyes (jaundice) a bulge in the tummy When to get medical advice See a GP as soon as possible if you develop sudden and severe abdominal pain, particularly if it lasts longer than a few hours or is accompanied by other symptoms, such as jaundice and a high temperature. If you're unable to contact a GP immediately, phone your local out-of-hours service or call NHS 111 for advice. It's important for acute cholecystitis to be diagnosed as soon as possible, as there's a risk of serious complications developing if it's not treated promptly. What causes acute cholecystitis? The causes of acute cholecystitis can be grouped into 2 main categories: calculous cholecystitis and acalculous cholecystitis. Calculous cholecystitis Calculous cholecystitis is the most common, and usually less serious, type of acute cholecystitis. It accounts for around 95% of all cases. Calculous cholecystitis develops when the main opening to the gallbladder, the cystic duct, gets blocked by a gallstone or a substance known as biliary sludge. Biliary sludge is a mixture of bile, a liquid produced by the liver that helps digest fats, and small cholesterol and salt crystals. The blockage in the cystic duct causes bile to build up in the gallbladder, increasing the pressure inside it and causing it to become inflamed. An inflamed gallbladder can sometimes become infected by bacteria. Acalculous cholecystitis Acalculous cholecystitis is gallbladder inflammation without gallstones. It's less common, but usually more serious, than calculous cholecystitis. The exact cause of acalculous cholecystitis is not known, but it's usually a complication of a serious illness, infection or injury that damages the gallbladder. A combination of risk factors may lead to acalculous cholecystitis, including accidental damage to the gallbladder during major surgery, serious injuries or burns , sepsis , severe malnutrition or dehydration . Diagnosing acute cholecystitis If you have severe tummy pain, a GP will probably carry out a simple test called Murphy's sign. You'll be asked to breathe in deeply with the GP's hand pressed on your tummy, just below your rib cage. Your gallbladder will move downwards as you breathe in. If you have cholecystitis, you'll experience sudden pain as your gallbladder reaches your doctor's hand. If your symptoms suggest you have acute cholecystitis, your GP will refer you to hospital immediately for further tests and treatment. Tests you may have in hospital include: blood tests – to check for signs of inflammation in your body an ultrasound scan of your tummy – to check for gallstones or other signs of a problem with your gallbladder Treating acute cholecystitis If you're diagnosed with acute cholecystitis, you'll probably need to be admitted to hospital for treatment. Initial treatment Initial treatment will usually involve: not eating or drinking (fasting) to take the strain off your gallbladder receiving fluids through a drip directly into a vein (intravenously) to prevent dehydration taking medicine to relieve your pain You'll also be given antibiotics if it's thought you have an infection. These often need to be continued for up to a week, during which time you may need to stay in hospital, or you may be able to go home. Surgery Removing your gallbladder may be recommended at some point after initial treatment to prevent acute cholecystitis coming back and reduce your risk of developing potentially serious complications. This type of surgery is known as a cholecystectomy . There are 2 main types of cholecystectomy: open cholecystectomy – where the gallbladder is removed through a single cut in the tummy laparoscopic cholecystectomy – keyhole surgery where the gallbladder is removed using special surgical instruments inserted through a number of small cuts in your abdomen If you're fit enough to have surgery, your doctors will decide when the best time to remove your gallbladder is. A laparoscopic cholecystectomy is often recommended within 1 week of confirming acute cholecystitis. Some people who have had their gallbladder removed have symptoms of bloating and diarrhoea after eating certain foods, but it's possible to lead a perfectly normal life without a gallbladder. The organ can be useful, but it's not essential as your liver will still produce bile to digest food. Find out more about recovering from gallbladder removal Alternatives to surgery Sometimes surgery may not be an option – for example, if you have another condition that makes surgery unsuitable. If surgery is not an option, you may be offered a procedure to drain away the fluid that has collected in your gallbladder. A narrow tube is inserted into the gallbladder to make an opening for the fluid to drain. This can be done through a cut made in the skin of your tummy, or using an endoscopic procedure (through your mouth and into the stomach). Possible complications Without appropriate treatment, acute cholecystitis can sometimes lead to potentially life-threatening complications. The main complications of acute cholecystitis are: the death of gallbladder tissue (gangrenous cholecystitis) – which can cause a serious infection that could spread throughout the body the gallbladder splitting open (perforated gallbladder) – which can spread the infection within your tummy (peritonitis) or lead to a build-up of pus (abscess) Emergency surgery to remove the gallbladder is needed to treat these complications in about 2 or 3 in every 10 cases of acute cholecystitis. Preventing acute cholecystitis It's not always possible to prevent acute cholecystitis, but you can lower your risk of developing it by reducing your risk of getting gallstones. One of the main things you can do to lower your chances of getting gallstones is to adopt a healthy, balanced diet and reduce the number of high-cholesterol foods you eat, as cholesterol is thought to contribute to the formation of gallstones. Living with overweight or obesity also increases your risk of developing gallstones. You should therefore control your weight by eating a healthy diet and exercising regularly . But low-calorie rapid weight loss diets should be avoided because there's evidence they can disrupt your bile chemistry and actually increase your risk of developing gallstones. A more gradual weight loss plan is best. Find out more about preventing gallstones The gallbladder The gallbladder is a small pear-shaped organ located beneath the liver. Its main purpose is to store and concentrate bile. The liver produces bile, a liquid that helps digest fats and carries toxins excreted by the liver. Bile is passed from the liver through a series of channels called bile ducts into the gallbladder, where it's stored. The gallbladder releases bile into the digestive system when it's needed. It's an organ that's useful, but not essential, and it can be safely removed without interfering with your ability to digest food. Page last reviewed: 21 February 2023 Next review due: 21 February 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Acute kidney injury (AKI) is where your kidneys suddenly stop working properly. It can range from minor loss of kidney function to complete kidney failure. AKI normally happens as a complication of another serious illness. It's not the result of a physical blow to the kidneys, as the name might suggest. This type of kidney damage is usually seen in older people who are unwell with other conditions and the kidneys are also affected. It's essential that AKI is detected early and treated promptly. Without quick treatment, abnormal levels of salts and chemicals can build up in the body, which affects the ability of other organs to work properly. If the kidneys shut down completely, this may require temporary support from a dialysis machine, or lead to death. AKI can also affect children and young people. Find out more from infoKID about AKI in children Symptoms of acute kidney injury Symptoms of AKI include: feeling sick or being sick diarrhoea dehydration peeing less than usual confusion drowsiness Even if it does not progress to complete kidney failure, AKI needs to be taken seriously. It has an effect on the whole body, changes how some medicines are handled by the body, and could make some existing illnesses more serious. AKI is different from chronic kidney disease , where the kidneys gradually lose function over a long period of time. Who's at risk of acute kidney injury? You're more likely to get AKI if: you're aged 65 or over you already have a kidney problem, such as chronic kidney disease you have a long-term disease, such as heart failure , liver disease or diabetes you're dehydrated or unable to maintain your fluid intake independently you have a blockage in your urinary tract (or are at risk of this) you have a severe infection or sepsis you're taking certain medicines, including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) , such as ibuprofen, or blood pressure medicines, such as ACE inhibitors or diuretics; diuretics help the kidneys get rid of extra fluid from the body, but may become less helpful when a person is dehydrated or suffering from a severe illness you're given aminoglycosides – a type of antibiotic that's usually only given in hospital; these medicines are only likely to increase the risk of AKI if you're dehydrated or ill Causes of acute kidney injury Most cases of AKI are caused by reduced blood flow to the kidneys, usually in someone who's already unwell with another health condition. This reduced blood flow could be caused by: low blood volume after bleeding, excessive vomiting or diarrhoea, or severe dehydration the heart pumping out less blood than normal as a result of heart failure , liver failure or sepsis certain medicines that reduce blood pressure or blood flow to the kidneys, such as ACE inhibitors, certain diuretics or NSAIDs AKI can also be caused by a problem with the kidney itself, such as inflammation of the filters in the kidney ( glomerulonephritis ), the blood vessels ( vasculitis ), or other structures in the kidney. This may be caused by a reaction to some medicines, infections or the liquid dye used in some types of X-rays. It may sometimes be the result of a blockage affecting the drainage of the kidneys, such as: an enlarged prostate a tumour in the pelvis, such as an ovarian or bladder tumour kidney stones Diagnosing acute kidney injury A doctor may suspect AKI if you: are in an "at risk" group and suddenly fall ill get symptoms of AKI AKI is usually diagnosed with a blood test to measure your levels of creatinine, a chemical waste product produced by the muscles. If there's a lot of creatinine in your blood, it means your kidneys are not working as well as they should. You may also be asked to give a pee sample. Find out more from InfoKID about AKI in children Investigating the underlying cause Urine can be tested for protein, blood cells, sugar and waste products, which may give clues to the underlying cause. Doctors also need to know about: any other symptoms, such as signs of sepsis or signs of heart failure any other medical conditions any medicine that's been taken in the past week, as some medicines can cause AKI An ultrasound scan should reveal if the cause is a blockage in the urinary system, such as an enlarged prostate or bladder tumour. Treating acute kidney injury Treatment of AKI depends on what's causing your illness and how severe it is. You may need: to increase your intake of water and other fluids if you're dehydrated antibiotics if you have an infection to stop taking certain medicines (at least until the problem is sorted) a urinary catheter, a thin tube used to drain the bladder if there's a blockage You may need to go to hospital for some treatments. Most people with AKI make a full recovery, but some people go on to develop chronic kidney disease or long-term kidney failure as a result. In severe cases, dialysis – where a machine filters the blood to rid the body of harmful waste, extra salt and water – may be needed. Preventing acute kidney injury Those at risk of AKI should be monitored with regular blood tests if they become unwell or start new medicine. It's also useful to check how much pee you're passing. Any warning signs of AKI, such as vomiting or producing little pee, require immediate investigation for AKI and treatment. People who are dehydrated or at risk of dehydration may need to be given fluids through a drip. Any medicine that seems to be making the problem worse or directly damaging the kidneys needs to be stopped, at least temporarily. Complications of acute kidney injury The most serious complications of acute kidney injury include: high levels of potassium in the blood – in severe cases, this can lead to muscle weakness, paralysis and heart rhythm problems too much fluid in the body, which can cause build-up of fluid in the arms and legs ( oedema ) or in the lungs (pulmonary oedema) acidic blood (metabolic acidosis) – which can cause nausea, vomiting, drowsiness and breathlessness chronic kidney disease Page last reviewed: 08 September 2022 Next review due: 08 September 2025</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Leukaemia is cancer of the white blood cells. Acute leukaemia means it progresses quickly and aggressively, and usually requires immediate treatment. Acute leukaemia is classified according to the type of white blood cells affected. The 2 main types of white blood cells are: monocytes and granulocytes, which come from myeloid stem cells lymphocytes, which come from lymphoid stem cells This topic focuses on acute myeloid leukaemia (AML), which is an aggressive cancer of the monocyte or granulocyte cells. The following types of leukaemia are covered separately: acute lymphoblastic leukaemia chronic myeloid leukaemia chronic lymphocytic leukaemia Symptoms of AML The symptoms of AML usually develop over a few weeks and become worse over time. Symptoms can include: looking pale or "washed out" feeling tired or weak breathlessness frequent infections unusual and frequent bruising or bleeding, such as bleeding gums or nosebleeds losing weight without trying to Seeking medical advice Speak to a GP if you or your child have possible symptoms of AML. Although it's highly unlikely that leukaemia is the cause, these symptoms should be investigated. If your GP thinks you may have leukaemia, they'll arrange blood tests to check your blood cells. If the tests suggest there's a problem, you'll be urgently referred to a specialist in treating blood conditions (haematologist) for further tests and treatment. Find out more about diagnosing AML What causes AML? It's not clear exactly what causes AML and, in most cases, there's no identifiable cause. But some things can increase your risk of getting AML, including: previous chemotherapy or radiotherapy exposure to very high levels of radiation (including previous radiotherapy treatment) smoking and other exposure to benzene, a chemical used in manufacturing that's also found in cigarette smoke having a blood disorder or some genetic conditions, such as Down's syndrome Find out more about the causes of AML Who's affected AML is a rare type of cancer, with around 3,100 people diagnosed with it each year in the UK. The risk of developing AML increases with age. It's most common in people over 75. How AML is treated Treatment for AML needs to begin as soon as possible, as it can develop quickly. Chemotherapy is the main treatment for AML. It's used to kill as many leukaemia cells in your body as possible and reduce the risk of the condition coming back (relapsing). In some cases, intensive chemotherapy and radiotherapy may be needed, in combination with a bone marrow or stem cell transplant . Find out more about treating AML Help and support There are organisations that offer information, advice and support if you or a family member has been diagnosed with AML. These include: Leukaemia Care – you can also call their freephone helpline on 08088 010 444, or email support@leukaemiacare.org.uk Cancer Research UK Macmillan Cancer Support Page last reviewed: 04 October 2022 Next review due: 04 October 2025 Next : Symptoms</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Acute pancreatitis is a condition where the pancreas becomes inflamed (swollen) over a short period of time. The pancreas is a small organ, located behind the stomach, that helps with digestion. Most people with acute pancreatitis start to feel better within about a week and have no further problems. But some people with severe acute pancreatitis can go on to develop serious complications. Acute pancreatitis is different to chronic pancreatitis , where the pancreas has become permanently damaged from inflammation over many years. Symptoms of acute pancreatitis The most common symptoms of acute pancreatitis include: suddenly getting severe pain in the centre of your tummy (abdomen) feeling or being sick a high temperature of 38C or more (fever) Read more about the symptoms of acute pancreatitis and diagnosing acute pancreatitis . When to get medical help See a GP immediately if you suddenly develop severe abdominal pain. If this isn't possible, contact NHS 111 for advice. Causes of acute pancreatitis Acute pancreatitis is most often linked to: gallstones drinking too much alcohol But sometimes the cause is not known. By reducing how much alcohol you drink and altering your diet to make gallstones less likely, you can reduce your chances of developing acute pancreatitis. Read more about the causes of acute pancreatitis and preventing acute pancreatitis . How it's treated Treatment for acute pancreatitis aims to help control the condition and manage any symptoms. This usually involves admission to hospital. You may be given fluids directly into a vein (intravenous fluids), pain relief, liquid food through a tube in your tummy and oxygen through tubes in your nose. Most people with acute pancreatitis get better within a week and are well enough to leave hospital after a few days. Recovery can take longer in severe cases, as some people can develop complications. Read more about treating acute pancreatitis and the possible complications of acute pancreatitis . Page last reviewed: 24 May 2022 Next review due: 24 May 2025 Next : Symptoms</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is a life-threatening illness that can happen when your lungs are not working properly. ARDS is usually a complication of other serious conditions and is treated in hospital. Who is at risk of getting acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) usually affects people who are already unwell. Causes of ARDS can include: sepsis infections such as pneumonia acute pancreatitis accidentally inhaling vomit or food drowning smoke inhalation severe injuries having blood transfusions having a lung transplant Symptoms of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) Symptoms of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) include: shortness of breath taking short, fast breaths Immediate action required: Call 999 or go to A&amp;E immediately if you or someone else: have severe difficulty breathing, for example, not being able to get words out, choking, or gasping have sudden shortness of breath and pain in your arms, back, neck or jaw have sudden shortness of breath and your chest feels tight or heavy have sudden shortness of breath and you're feeling sick or being sick have sudden shortness of breath and you're coughing up blood have sudden shortness of breath and you have pain or swelling in 1 of your legs Find your nearest A&amp;E Information: Do not drive to A&amp;E. Ask someone to drive you or call 999 and ask for an ambulance. Bring any medicines you take with you. Treatment for acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is treated in hospital, usually in an intensive care unit (ICU) . Treatment may include: oxygen, which you breathe in using a mask ventilation, where a machine is used to breathe for you medicines, such as antibiotics to treat infection fluids given through a vein ARDS is a life-threatening condition and cannot always be cured. There's a chance someone who has it may die. Complications of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) ARDS can have long-term effects, such as: shortness of breath muscle weakness pain Page last reviewed: 12 July 2023 Next review due: 12 July 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of Addison's disease Many of the symptoms of Addison’s disease are the same as the symptoms of other conditions. Symptoms of Addison’s disease include: extreme tiredness (fatigue) areas of skin that are darker than surrounding skin – this may be harder to see on brown or black skin loss of appetite, weight loss, tummy pain, feeling or being sick and cravings for salty foods feeling dizzy or light-headed when standing up joint pain, muscle weakness and muscle cramps headache a slightly raised temperature feeling thirsty and needing to pee a lot difficulty concentrating anxiety and depression Addison’s disease most commonly affects adults between the ages of 30 and 50, but it can sometimes affect children. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you think you might have Addison’s disease Tests for Addison's disease If a GP thinks you or your child might have Addison’s disease, they’ll refer you to a specialist. This is usually a hormone specialist (endocrinologist), although children are often referred to a doctor who specialises in the treatment of children (paediatrician). The specialist will ask about your symptoms and you may have: a test to see how well your adrenal glands are working by checking samples of your blood before and after having an injection of a medicine called Synacthen blood tests to check your hormone levels and how well your thyroid gland is working Treatments for Addison's disease There’s currently no cure for Addison’s disease, but there are medicines that can help manage the condition. If you have Addison’s disease, your adrenal glands are not producing enough hormones, including types of hormones called steroids. The main treatment is steroid medicine to replace the missing hormones your body needs. Medicines you may be given include: hydrocortisone prednisolone fludrocortisone You’ll usually need to take your medicine every day for the rest of your life. It’s important you always have enough to avoid running out. At certain times you may need to take extra medicine, such as when you’re unwell, about to have surgery, or during stressful periods like when taking exams. Your specialist will be able to advise you about this. If you’re taking steroids, you should carry a steroid emergency card with you at all times. This tells healthcare professionals you have Addison’s disease and you take steroid medicine that should not be stopped suddenly. You can also get jewellery and wristbands with details of your condition and the medicine you take engraved or printed on them. Information: Find out more Managing Addison’s (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Steroid emergency cards (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Medical jewellery (Addison's Disease Self-Help Group) Complications of Addison's disease Adrenal crisis is the most serious complication of Addison’s disease. During adrenal crisis your symptoms get worse very quickly. This can be triggered by things like an infection, an accident or injury, or surgery. It can cause problems such as: severe dehydration low blood pressure (hypotension) seizures (fits) loss of consciousness stroke your heart suddenly stopping (cardiac arrest) Adrenal crisis is a medical emergency and can usually be treated with an injection of steroid medicine. You should be given an emergency kit so you can give the injection yourself if needed. Your specialist may also give you or your carer training in what to do if you have adrenal crisis. Immediate action required: Call 999 if: You have Addison's disease and the symptoms suddenly get worse or you: have a fast heart rate feel very dizzy or light-headed (particularly when standing up after sitting or lying down) have severe tummy pain or pain in the side have muscle weakness, pain or spasms have a headache that does not go away feel sick (nausea) or vomit feel very drowsy, irritable or confused have a seizure (fit) lose consciousness These could be signs of adrenal crisis. It’s important to call 999 even if you’ve given yourself an emergency steroid injection. Information: Find out more What is adrenal crisis (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Emergency injection for treating adrenal crisis (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) How Addison’s disease affects your life Addison’s disease is a serious condition that can be challenging to live with. You’ll need to remember to take your steroid medicine every day and there may be times when your symptoms get worse or you need emergency treatment. But with treatment, you can have a good quality of life with a normal life expectancy. You’ll have appointments with your specialist to discuss things like: your symptoms how well your medicine is working how confident you feel about managing your condition Addison’s disease and pregnancy It’s very important Addison’s disease is well managed during pregnancy otherwise it can cause serious problems, including an increased risk of miscarriage. If you’re planning a pregnancy, your specialist can tell you what you need to do to manage your condition and keep healthy during pregnancy. Information: Find out more Travelling with Addison's (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Children and young people (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Causes of Addison’s disease The most common cause of Addison’s disease is the immune system mistakenly attacking and damaging the adrenal glands. This means the adrenal glands are unable to produce hormones that your body needs. Other causes of Addison’s disease include: your adrenal glands being bigger than usual at birth (congenital adrenal hyperplasia) infections, such as tuberculosis , meningitis , flu , cytomegalovirus and HIV , which can damage your adrenal glands surgery to remove your adrenal glands Help and support for Addison's disease If you or your child have Addison’s disease, healthcare professionals will support you throughout your treatment. You may also find it helpful to get support from other people with Addison’s disease, or parents of children with the condition. Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group (ADSHG) The charity Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group (ADSHG) provides a range of support and information for people affected by Addison’s disease. Website: www.addisonsdisease.org.uk What is Addison’s disease? (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Helpful resources (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Addison’s sanctuary of support (Addison’s Disease Self-Help Group) Recording information about you and your condition If you or your child have Addison’s disease, your care team will pass information on to the National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service (NCARDRS) . This helps scientists look for better ways to prevent and treat this condition. You can opt out of the register at any time. Page last reviewed: 19 September 2025 Next review due: 19 September 2028</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>Adenomyosis is a condition where the lining of the womb (uterus) starts growing into the muscle in the wall of the womb. There are treatments that can help with any symptoms. Adenomyosis is more commonly diagnosed in women over the age of 30. It can affect anyone who has periods. Credit: Multimedia Team - nhs.uk Symptoms of adenomyosis Some symptoms of adenomyosis affect your periods, such as: painful periods – the pain may be severe and stop you from doing your usual activities heavy bleeding during your period Other symptoms can happen any time in your menstrual cycle, such as: pelvic pain (pain in the lower part of your tummy) bloating, heaviness or fullness in your tummy (abdomen) pain during sex Some people with adenomyosis have no symptoms. Information: Endometriosis is a different condition where tissue similar to the lining of the womb grows in other places, such as the ovaries or fallopian tubes. Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: your pelvic pain or period pain is severe or worse than usual, and painkillers have not helped You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: your periods become more painful, heavier or irregular you have pain during sex heavy periods are affecting your life or you've had them for some time you've been feeling bloated for a while (about 3 weeks) you bleed between periods or after sex What happens at your GP appointment The GP may ask about your periods if you have symptoms of adenomyosis. They may feel your tummy to see if there’s any swelling or bloating. You can ask for a female doctor when you book your appointment. The doctor might also ask to do an internal examination, to check your vagina and cervix (the opening between the vagina and the womb). You can have a friend, family member or other member of staff in the room with you during your examination if you want. Sometimes further tests are needed to find out what’s causing your symptoms, or to rule out similar conditions such as endometriosis. Tests may include: ultrasound scan MRI scan Treatments for adenomyosis If you’re diagnosed with adenomyosis, there are treatments that can help ease your symptoms. Treatments include: the IUS (intrauterine system, also called Mirena or hormonal coil), which thins the womb lining, making your periods lighter and less painful other types of hormonal contraception if you cannot or do not want to have an IUS, such as the progestogen-only pill , the combined pill or the contraceptive patch medicines such as tranexamic acid or NSAIDs If these treatments do not work, you may need surgery. This could be a hysterectomy , or surgery to remove the lining of your womb (endometrial ablation). How to ease symptoms of adenomyosis There are things that can help with period pain or pelvic pain caused by adenomyosis. Do use a heat pad or hot water bottle wrapped in a tea towel on your tummy try a TENS machine – a small device that uses mild electrical impulses to reduce pain take painkillers like paracetamol or ibuprofen Who is more likely to get adenomyosis? It's not clear what causes adenomyosis. You may be more likely to get it if you are over the age of 30 and have given birth. Page last reviewed: 17 July 2023 Next review due: 17 July 2026</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>Albinism affects the production of melanin, the pigment that colours skin, hair and eyes. It's a lifelong condition, but it does not get worse over time. People with albinism have a reduced amount of melanin, or no melanin at all. This can affect their colouring and their eyesight. People with albinism often have white or very light blonde hair, although some have brown or red hair. The exact colour depends on how much melanin their body produces. Very pale skin that burns easily in the sun and does not usually tan is also typical of albinism. Eye problems The reduced amount of melanin can cause eye problems. This is because melanin is involved in the development of the retina, the thin layer of cells at the back of the eye. Possible eye problems linked to albinism include: poor eyesight – either short-sightedness or long-sightedness , and low vision (sight loss that cannot be corrected) astigmatism – where the cornea (clear layer at the front of the eye) is not perfectly curved or the lens is an abnormal shape, causing blurred vision photophobia – where the eyes are sensitive to light nystagmus – where the eyes move involuntarily from side to side, causing reduced vision; you do not see the world as "wobbling" because your brain adapts to your eye movement squint – where the eyes point in different directions Some young children with albinism may appear clumsy. This is because problems with their eyesight can make some movements difficult for them, such as picking up an object. This should improve as they get older. How albinism is passed on The 2 main types of albinism are: oculocutaneous albinism (OCA) – the most common type, affecting the skin, hair and eyes ocular albinism (OA) – a rarer type that mainly affects the eyes Autosomal recessive inheritance In all types of OCA and some types of OA, albinism is passed on in an autosomal recessive inheritance pattern. This means a child has to get 2 copies of the gene that causes albinism (1 from each parent) to have the condition. If both parents carry the gene, there's a 1 in 4 chance that their child will have albinism and a 1 in 2 chance that their child will be a carrier. Carriers do not have albinism but can pass on the gene. X-linked inheritance Most types of OA are passed on in an X-linked inheritance pattern. This pattern affects boys and girls differently: girls who get the albinism gene usually become carriers only, while boys who get it will have albinism. When a mother is a carrier of an X-linked type of albinism, each of her daughters has a 1 in 2 chance of becoming a carrier. Each of her sons has a 1 in 2 chance of having albinism. When a father has an X-linked type of albinism, his daughters will become carriers, and his sons will not have albinism and will not be carriers. Genetic counselling If you have a history of albinism in your family or you have a child with the condition, you may want to talk to a GP about getting a referral for genetic counselling. A genetic counsellor provides information, support and advice about genetic conditions. For example, you can discuss with them how you inherited albinism and the chances of passing it on. Read more about genetic and genomic testing Diagnosing albinism Albinism is usually obvious from a baby's appearance when they're born. Your baby's hair, skin and eyes may be examined to look for signs of missing pigment. As albinism can cause a number of eye problems, your baby may be referred to an eye specialist (ophthalmologist) for tests. Electrodiagnostic testing is also sometimes used to help diagnose albinism. This is where small electrodes are stuck to the scalp to test the connections of the eyes to the part of the brain that controls vision. Treatments for eye problems due to albinism Although there's no cure for the eye problems caused by albinism, there are a number of treatments, such as glasses and contact lenses, that can improve vision. A child with albinism may also need extra help and support at school. Glasses and contact lenses As a child with albinism gets older, they'll need regular eye tests , and it's likely they'll need to wear glasses or contact lenses to correct vision problems. Low-vision aids Vision aids include: large-print or high-contrast books and printed materials magnifying lenses a small telescope or telescopic lenses that attach to glasses to read writing in the distance, such as on a school whiteboard large computer screens software that can turn speech into typing or vice versa tablets and phones that allow you to magnify the display to make writing and images easier to see The Royal National Institute of Blind People (RNIB) has more information about living with low vision, including a section on education and learning Photophobia or sensitivity to light Sunglasses, tinted glasses and wearing a wide-brimmed hat outside can help with sensitivity to light. Nystagmus There's currently no cure for nystagmus (where the eyes move from side to side involuntarily). However, it is not painful and does not get worse. Certain toys or games may help a child make the most of the vision they have. An ophthalmologist will be able to provide further advice. Surgery, involving dividing and then reattaching some of the eye muscles, may sometimes be an option. Squint and lazy eye The main treatments for squints are glasses, eye exercises, surgery and injections into the eye muscles. If your child has developed a lazy eye, they may benefit from wearing a patch over their "good" eye to encourage their other eye to work harder. Read more about treatments for squints Reducing the risk of sunburn and skin cancer Because people with albinism lack melanin in their skin, they're at increased risk of getting sunburn and skin cancer . If you have albinism, you should wear sunscreen with a high sun-protection factor (SPF). An SPF of 30 or more will provide the best protection. You should also spend time in the shade when the sun is strongest and cover up with suitable clothing and sunglasses. It's also a good idea to look out for skin changes, such as: a new mole, growth or lump any moles, freckles or patches of skin that change in size, shape or colour Report these to a doctor as soon as possible. Skin cancer is much easier to treat if it's found early. Help and support There's usually no reason why someone with albinism cannot do well in schooling, further education and employment. With appropriate help and support, children with albinism can attend a mainstream school. You might like to talk to other people with albinism. The Albinism Fellowship runs meetings around the UK, and has phone and email support . Information about you If you or your child has albinism, your clinical team will pass information on to the National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service (NCARDRS) . The NCARDRS helps scientists look for better ways to prevent and treat this condition. You can opt out of the register at any time. Page last reviewed: 26 September 2023 Next review due: 26 September 2026</text><label>4</label></item><item><text>Alcohol misuse is when you drink in a way that's harmful, or when you're dependent on alcohol. To keep health risks from alcohol to a low level, both men and women are advised not to regularly drink more than 14 units a week. A unit of alcohol is 8g or 10ml of pure alcohol, which is about: half a pint of lower to normal-strength lager/beer/cider (ABV 3.6%) a single small shot measure (25ml) of spirits (25ml, ABV 40%) A small glass (125ml, ABV 12%) of wine contains about 1.5 units of alcohol. Find out more about alcohol units Low-risk drinking advice To keep your risk of alcohol-related harm low: men and women are advised not to drink more than 14 units of alcohol a week on a regular basis if you drink as much as 14 units a week, it's best to spread this evenly over 3 or more days if you're trying to reduce the amount of alcohol you drink, it's a good idea to have several alcohol-free days each week if you're pregnant or trying to become pregnant, the safest approach is to not drink alcohol at all to keep risks to your baby to a minimum Regular or frequent drinking means drinking alcohol most days and weeks. The risk to your health is increased by drinking any amount of alcohol on a regular basis. Risks of alcohol misuse Short term The short-term risks of alcohol misuse include: accidents and injuries requiring hospital treatment, such as a head injury violent behaviour and being a victim of violence unprotected sex that could potentially lead to unplanned pregnancy or sexually transmitted infections (STIs) loss of personal possessions, such as wallets, keys or mobile phones alcohol poisoning – this may lead to vomiting, fits (seizures) and falling unconscious People who binge drink (drink heavily over a short period of time) are more likely to behave recklessly and are at greater risk of being in an accident. Long term Persistent alcohol misuse increases your risk of serious health conditions, including: heart disease stroke liver disease liver cancer bowel cancer mouth cancer breast cancer pancreatitis damage to the brain, which can lead to problems with thinking and memory As well as causing serious health problems, long-term alcohol misuse can lead to social problems for some people, such as unemployment, divorce, domestic abuse and homelessness. If someone loses control over their drinking and has an excessive desire to drink, it's known as dependent drinking (alcoholism). Dependent drinking usually affects a person's quality of life and relationships, but they may not always find it easy to see or accept this. Severely dependent drinkers are often able to tolerate very high levels of alcohol in amounts that would dangerously affect or even kill some people. A dependent drinker usually experiences physical and psychological withdrawal symptoms if they suddenly cut down or stop drinking, including: hand tremors – "the shakes" sweating seeing things that are not real (visual hallucinations ) depression anxiety difficulty sleeping (insomnia) This often leads to "relief drinking" to avoid withdrawal symptoms. Find out more about the risks of alcohol misuse Am I drinking too much alcohol? You could be misusing alcohol if: you feel you should cut down on your drinking other people have been criticising your drinking you feel guilty or bad about your drinking you need a drink first thing in the morning to steady your nerves or get rid of a hangover Someone you know may be misusing alcohol if: they regularly drink more than 14 units of alcohol a week they're sometimes unable to remember what happened the night before because of their drinking they fail to do what was expected of them as a result of their drinking (for example, missing an appointment or work because they're drunk or hungover) Getting help If you're concerned about your drinking or someone else's, a good first step is to see a GP. They'll be able to discuss the services and treatments available. Your alcohol intake may be assessed using tests, such as the: Alcohol use disorders identification test (PDF, 224kb) – a widely used screening test that can help determine whether you need to change your drinking habits Alcohol use disorders identification test consumption (PDF, 382kb) – a simpler test to check whether your drinking has reached dangerous levels As well as the NHS, there are a number of charities and support groups across the UK that provide support and advice for people with an alcohol misuse problem. For example, you may want to contact: Drinkline national alcohol helpline on 0300 123 1110 Alcohol Change UK Alcoholics Anonymous helpline on 0800 9177 650 Al-Anon Family Groups helpline on 0800 0086 811 Treating alcohol misuse How alcohol misuse is treated depends on how much alcohol a person is drinking. Treatment options include: counselling – including self-help groups and talking therapies, such as cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) medicines detoxification – this involves a nurse or doctor supporting you to safely stop drinking; this can be done by helping you slowly cut down over time or by giving you medicines to prevent withdrawal symptoms There are 2 main types of medicines to help people stop drinking. The first is to help stop withdrawal symptoms and is given in reducing doses over a short period of time. The most common of these medicines is chlordiazapoxide (Librium). The second is a medicine to reduce any urge you may have to drink. The most common medicines used for this are acamprosate and naltrexone. These are both given at a fixed dose, and you'll usually be on them for 6 to 12 months. Further reading Alcohol units Carers Trust: caring for an alcoholic Tips for cutting down on your drinking Alcohol and pregnancy The Department of Health and Social Care recommends pregnant women and women trying to conceive should avoid drinking alcohol. Drinking in pregnancy can lead to long-term harm to the baby, and the risk increases the more you drink. The Chief Medical Officers for the UK recommend that if you're pregnant or planning to become pregnant, the safest approach is not to drink alcohol at all to keep the risk to your baby to a minimum. If you're worried about alcohol use during pregnancy, talk to your doctor or midwife. If you're trying to conceive, your partner should drink no more than 14 units of alcohol a week, which should be spread evenly over 3 days or more. Drinking alcohol excessively can affect the quality of his sperm. Page last reviewed: 04 October 2022 Next review due: 04 October 2025 Next : Risks</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>Alcohol poisoning can happen when you drink alcohol quicker than your body can process it. It can make you seriously ill and you may need to go to hospital for treatment. Symptoms of alcohol poisoning Symptoms start after drinking a lot of alcohol and may include: confusion slurring words or being unable to speak being unable to coordinate movement, for example, being unable to stand, walk, or pick things up being sick peeing or pooing yourself pale or blue-tinged skin - on black or brown skin this may be easier to see inside the lips, on the gums and under the fingernails slow or irregular breathing having a seizure or fit loss of consciousness Immediate action required: Call 999 if: you think someone has alcohol poisoning you or someone else has had a seizure or fit someone has lost consciousness someone has stopped breathing Information: Do not drive yourself to A&amp;E. The person you speak to at 999 will give you advice about what to do. Things you can do to help someone who has drunk too much alcohol Do stay with them because there's a risk they could choke on their own sick or stop breathing sit them up if they're awake, or put them in the recovery position if they've passed out and check they're breathing properly give them water to sip if they're able to swallow keep them warm with a jacket or blanket Don’t do not let them drink more alcohol do not give them coffee or drinks containing caffeine because this can dehydrate people with alcohol poisoning do not put them in a cold shower or bath because there's a risk they could get too cold, fall or lose consciousness in the water do not try to make them sick Treatment for alcohol poisoning You'll need to go to hospital to be monitored if you have alcohol poisoning. It can cause serious complications, like liver and heart failure, which can be fatal. You may be given fluids, which may be given into your veins with a drip. You may also be given help with your breathing until the effects of the alcohol wear off. Causes of alcohol poisoning Alcohol poisoning is usually caused by binge drinking, which is where you have a lot of alcohol in one drinking session. It can happen when you drink alcohol faster than your body can filter it out of your blood. Having too much alcohol in your blood stops your body working properly and can be life-threatening. Alcohol affects people differently. Some people may be able to drink more alcohol than others, with fewer effects. Find out more about the risks of drinking too much Information: Find out more Alcohol support Alcohol units Page last reviewed: 11 January 2023 Next review due: 11 January 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Alcohol-related liver disease (ARLD) refers to liver damage caused by excess alcohol intake. There are several stages of severity and a range of associated symptoms. Symptoms of alcohol-related liver disease (ARLD) ARLD does not usually cause any symptoms until the liver has been severely damaged. When this happens, symptoms can include: feeling sick weight loss loss of appetite yellowing of the whites of the eyes or skin ( jaundice ) swelling in the ankles and tummy confusion or drowsiness vomiting blood or passing blood in your stools This means ARLD is frequently diagnosed during tests for other conditions, or at a stage of advanced liver damage. If you regularly drink alcohol to excess, tell your GP so they can check if your liver is damaged. Alcohol and the liver The liver is one of the most complex organs in the body. Its functions include: filtering toxins from the blood aiding digestion of food regulating blood sugar and cholesterol levels helping fight infection and disease The liver is very resilient and capable of regenerating itself. Each time your liver filters alcohol, some of the liver cells die. The liver can develop new cells, but prolonged alcohol misuse (drinking too much) over many years can reduce its ability to regenerate. This can result in serious and permanent damage to your liver. ARLD is common in the UK. The number of people with the condition has been increasing over the last few decades as a result of increasing levels of alcohol misuse. Read more about the causes of ARLD Stages of ARLD There are 3 main stages of ARLD, although there's often an overlap between each stage. These stages are explained here. Alcoholic fatty liver disease Drinking a large amount of alcohol, even for just a few days, can lead to a build-up of fats in the liver. This is called alcoholic fatty liver disease, and is the first stage of ARLD. Fatty liver disease rarely causes any symptoms, but it's an important warning sign that you're drinking at a harmful level. Fatty liver disease is reversible. If you stop drinking alcohol for some time (months or years), your liver should return to normal. Alcoholic hepatitis Alcoholic hepatitis, which is unrelated to infectious hepatitis , is a potentially serious condition that can be caused by alcohol misuse over a longer period. When this develops, it may be the first time a person is aware they're damaging their liver through alcohol. Less commonly, alcoholic hepatitis can occur if you drink a large amount of alcohol in a short period of time (binge drinking). The liver damage associated with mild alcoholic hepatitis is usually reversible if you stop drinking permanently. Severe alcoholic hepatitis, however, is a serious and life-threatening illness. Many people die from the condition each year in the UK, and some people only find out they have liver damage when their condition reaches this stage. Cirrhosis Cirrhosis is a stage of ARLD where the liver has become significantly scarred. Even at this stage, there may not be any obvious symptoms. It's generally not reversible, but stopping drinking alcohol immediately can prevent further damage and significantly increase your life expectancy. Treating alcohol-related liver disease (ARLD) There's currently no specific medical treatment for ARLD. The main treatment is to stop drinking, preferably for the rest of your life. This reduces the risk of further damage to your liver and gives it the best chance of recovering. If a person is dependent on alcohol, stopping drinking can be very difficult. But support, advice and medical treatment may be available through local alcohol addiction support services . A liver transplant may be required in severe cases where the liver has stopped functioning and does not improve when you stop drinking alcohol. You'll only be considered for a liver transplant if you have developed complications of cirrhosis despite having stopped drinking. All liver transplant units require people with ARLD to not drink alcohol while awaiting the transplant, and for the rest of their life. Complications Death rates linked to ARLD have risen considerably over the last few decades. Alcohol misuse is now one of the most common causes of death in the UK, along with smoking and high blood pressure . Life-threatening complications of ARLD include: internal (variceal) bleeding build-up of toxins in the brain (encephalopathy) fluid accumulation in the abdomen (ascites) with associated kidney failure liver cancer increased vulnerability to infection Read more about the complications of ARLD Preventing alcohol-related liver disease (ARLD) The most effective way to prevent ARLD is to stop drinking alcohol or stick to the recommended limits: men and women are advised not to regularly drink more than 14 units a week spread your drinking over 3 days or more if you drink as much as 14 units a week if you want to cut down, try to have several drink-free days each week A unit of alcohol is equal to about half a pint of normal-strength lager or a pub measure (25ml) of spirits. Even if you have been a heavy drinker for many years, reducing or stopping your alcohol intake will have important short-term and long-term benefits for your liver and overall health. See our alcohol advice pages for more information and support. Video: Liver disease In this video, consultant hepatologist Mark Wright explains liver disease and how not drinking alcohol can help. Media last reviewed: 8 October 2024 Media review due: 8 October 2027 Page last reviewed: 20 September 2022 Next review due: 20 September 2025 Next : Symptoms</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>Allergic rhinitis is where your nose gets irritated by something you're allergic to, such as pollen, causing sneezing and other symptoms. For most people it's easy to treat with medicines from a pharmacist. Symptoms of allergic rhinitis Common symptoms of allergic rhinitis are similar to a cold and include: sneezing an itchy nose a runny or blocked nose itchy, red and watery eyes a cough the roof of your mouth being itchy This usually happens within minutes of coming into contact with something you're allergic to. Causes of allergic rhinitis Allergic rhinitis is caused by an allergic reaction. Common allergies include: pollen from trees, grass and weeds ( hay fever ) house dust mites animals such as dogs and cats mould wood dust, flour dust and latex You're more likely to get an allergy if people in your family also have them or conditions such as eczema and asthma . Information: Allergic rhinitis is different from non-allergic rhinitis , which is caused by things like having a cold, very hot or cold temperatures and humidity. How you can treat allergic rhinitis yourself You can often treat allergic rhinitis without seeing a GP. If you can, try to avoid the things that trigger your allergies. A pharmacist can also advise you about medicines that can help, such as: antihistamines decongestant nasal sprays or drops to unblock your nose (decongestants should not be used by children under 6) salt water nasal sprays or solutions to rinse out the inside of your nose You can buy nasal sprays without a prescription, but they should not be used for more than a week as this can make your symptoms worse. Find a pharmacy How to clean your nose with a homemade salt water solution Boil a pint of water, then leave it to cool. Mix 1 teaspoon of salt and 1 teaspoon of bicarbonate of soda into the water. Wash your hands. Stand over a sink, cup the palm of 1 hand and pour a small amount of the solution into it. Sniff the water into 1 nostril at a time. Breathe through your mouth and allow the water to pour back into the sink. Try not to let the water go down the back of your throat. Repeat the first 5 steps up to 3 times a day (making a new solution each time) until your nose feels more comfortable. If you have a high temperature or you do not feel well enough to do your normal activities, try to stay at home and avoid contact with other people until you feel better. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you have allergic rhinitis and your symptoms get worse you also have asthma and it's getting worse your symptoms are affecting your sleep and everyday life you're not sure what's causing your symptoms treatments from a pharmacist are not working Treatments for allergic rhinitis from a GP If pharmacy medicines do not help ease your allergic rhinitis symptoms, a GP may prescribe a different medicine, such as prescription steroid nasal sprays or antihistamines . You may be referred to a specialist for further tests and treatment if it's not clear what's causing your symptoms or they're severe. Preventing allergic rhinitis If you have allergic rhinitis, it's not always possible to avoid the things you're allergic to. But there are steps you can take to try to help reduce your symptoms. Do wear wraparound sunglasses to protect your eyes from pollen use hypoallergenic bedding and covers, and wash bedding regularly at 60C and above dust with a damp cloth and use a vacuum with a HEPA filter wash pets at least once every 2 weeks and groom them outside regularly regularly wash your pet's bedding and clean any furniture they've been on keep your home dry and well-ventilated, and deal with any damp and condensation Don’t do not allow pets in bedrooms do not go outside or dry clothes outside when the pollen count is high, if possible Information: Find out more Allergy UK: living with an allergy Page last reviewed: 30 May 2022 Next review due: 30 May 2025</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>An allergy is where your body reacts to something that's normally harmless like pollen, dust or animal fur. The symptoms can be mild, but for some people they can be very serious. Causes of allergies Things that cause allergic reactions are called allergens. Common allergens include: tree and grass pollen ( hay fever ) house dust mites foods, such as peanuts, milk and eggs ( food allergy ) animals, particularly pets like cats and dogs insect stings, such as bee and wasp stings certain medicines Symptoms of an allergic reaction Symptoms of an allergic reaction can include: a runny nose or sneezing pain or tenderness around your cheeks, eyes or forehead coughing, wheezing or breathlessness itchy skin or a raised rash ( hives ) diarrhoea feeling or being sick swollen eyes, lips, mouth or throat Immediate action required: Call 999 if: your lips, mouth, throat or tongue suddenly become swollen you're breathing very fast or struggling to breathe (you may become very wheezy or feel like you're choking or gasping for air) your throat feels tight or you're struggling to swallow your skin, tongue or lips turn blue, grey or pale (if you have black or brown skin, this may be easier to see on the palms of your hands or soles of your feet) you suddenly become very confused, drowsy or dizzy someone faints and cannot be woken up a child is limp, floppy or not responding like they normally do (their head may fall to the side, backwards or forwards, or they may find it difficult to lift their head or focus on your face) You or the person who's unwell may also have a rash that's swollen, raised or itchy. These can be signs of a serious allergic reaction and may need immediate treatment in hospital. Find your nearest A&amp;E Information: If you have an adrenaline auto-injector If you or someone you're with is having a serious allergic reaction and has an adrenaline auto-injector (such as an EpiPen), you should use it immediately. Instructions are included on the side of the injector if you forget how to use it or someone else needs to give you the injection. Call 999 for an ambulance after using the injector, even if you or the person you're with seems to be feeling better. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you think you or your child may have an allergy What happens at your appointment A GP may arrange some allergy tests or refer you to a specialist allergy clinic to have them. Tests you may have include: a skin prick or patch test – where a small amount of the allergen is put on your skin to see if it reacts blood tests – to check for allergens that may be causing your symptoms a special diet where you avoid or eat less of a food you might be allergic to, to see if your symptoms get better Treatments for allergies Treatments for allergies include: trying to avoid the thing you're allergic to whenever possible medicines for mild allergic reactions like antihistamines , steroid tablets and steroid creams emergency medicines called adrenaline auto-injectors, such as an EpiPen, for severe allergic reactions desensitisation (immunotherapy) for severe allergic reactions – this involves carefully exposing you to the thing you're allergic to over time, so your body gradually gets used to it and does not react so badly (this should only be done by a medical professional) Your specialist will give you an allergy management plan that will explain how to manage your allergy. Information: Find out more Allergy UK: living with an allergy Page last reviewed: 02 August 2022 Next review due: 02 August 2025</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Altitude sickness can happen when you're at a high altitude. It usually gets better in a few days with rest, but it can sometimes be life-threatening and need treatment. Check if you're at risk of altitude sickness You can get altitude sickness if you're in a place that is at a high altitude (usually more than 2,500 metres above sea level). You're more likely to get it if you travel or climb to a high altitude quickly. You can get it in places like: Mount Everest in Nepal Mount Kilimanjaro in Tanzania some places in the Alps La Paz in Bolivia You cannot get altitude sickness in the UK. Information: Check your travel risk You can check if there's a risk of altitude sickness in a country or place you're travelling to on the TravelHealthPro website Symptoms of altitude sickness Symptoms of altitude sickness usually start 6 to 10 hours after being at a high altitude. The main symptoms include: a headache loss of appetite feeling or being sick feeling tired or exhausted dizziness difficulty sleeping Sometimes, the symptoms can develop into more serious symptoms that can be life-threatening. What to do if you get altitude sickness If you're at a high altitude and have symptoms of altitude sickness or feel unwell: tell someone who you're travelling with that you do not feel well rest at the same altitude until you feel better – do not travel or climb to a higher altitude you can take anti-sickness medicine or painkillers such as ibuprofen or paracetamol to ease symptoms Symptoms of altitude sickness usually get better in 1 to 3 days. If your symptoms have gone and you feel better, you can travel or climb to a higher altitude. Important: If your symptoms do not get better If your symptoms get worse or do not improve after 1 day, go to a lower altitude if you can. Try to go around 300 to 1,000 metres lower. Urgent advice: Get medical help immediately if: You are at a high altitude and you or someone else: have symptoms of altitude sickness and feel very unwell are confused have problems with balance or coordination are seeing or hearing things that are not real (hallucinations) feel short of breath, even when resting have a cough or are coughing up frothy or bloody spit have blue or grey skin, lips, tongue or nails (on brown or black skin this may be easier to see on the palms of the hands or the soles of the feet) are very sleepy or difficult to wake Go to a lower altitude straight away (around 300 to 1,000 metres lower) if you can. Treatment for altitude sickness Altitude sickness usually gets better without treatment if you rest. You may be given medicine to help ease symptoms. If your symptoms are more serious, you may be given: steroid medicine medicine to lower your blood pressure oxygen through a mask Rarely, you may need to be treated with oxygen in a special air-tight chamber (hyperbaric chamber) to increase the level of oxygen in your blood. How to reduce your risk of altitude sickness There are some things you can do to help reduce your risk of getting altitude sickness. Do travel or climb to a high altitude slowly to give your body time to get used to lower oxygen levels spend a few days at an altitude below 2,500 metres before going any higher have a rest day at the same altitude every 3 to 4 days (if you're at an altitude of 3,000 metres or more) drink enough water so you do not get dehydrated speak to a GP or travel clinic if you've had altitude sickness before or if you're travelling to a high altitude quickly – they may prescribe medicine to help prevent altitude sickness Don’t try not to travel from an altitude that's less than 1,200 metres to an altitude that's more than 3,500 metres in 1 day try not to fly directly to a place with a high altitude – if this is not possible, rest for 1 day before going any higher try not to sleep more than 500 metres higher than you slept the night before (if you're at an altitude of 3,000 metres or more) do not drink alcohol while travelling or climbing Page last reviewed: 31 July 2023 Next review due: 31 July 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Alzheimer's disease is the most common cause of dementia in the UK. Dementia is the name for a group of symptoms associated with an ongoing decline of brain functioning. It can affect memory, thinking skills and other mental abilities. The exact cause of Alzheimer's disease is not yet fully understood, although a number of things are thought to increase your risk of developing the condition. These include: increasing age a family history of the condition untreated depression , although depression can also be one of the symptoms of Alzheimer's disease lifestyle factors and conditions associated with cardiovascular disease Read more about the causes of Alzheimer's disease . Signs and symptoms of Alzheimer's disease Alzheimer's disease is a progressive condition, which means the symptoms develop gradually over many years and eventually become more severe. It affects multiple brain functions. The first sign of Alzheimer's disease is usually minor memory problems. For example, this could be forgetting about recent conversations or events, and forgetting the names of places and objects. As the condition develops, memory problems become more severe and further symptoms can develop, such as: confusion, disorientation and getting lost in familiar places difficulty planning or making decisions problems with speech and language problems moving around without assistance or performing self-care tasks behaviour changes, such as becoming aggressive or suspicious of others hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that are not there) and delusions (believing things that are untrue) low mood or anxiety Read more about the symptoms of Alzheimer's disease . Who is affected? Alzheimer's disease is most common in people over the age of 65. The risk of Alzheimer's disease and other types of dementia increases with age, affecting an estimated 1 in 14 people over the age of 65 and 1 in every 6 people over the age of 80. But around 1 in every 13 people with Alzheimer's disease are under the age of 65. This is called early- or young-onset Alzheimer's disease. Getting a diagnosis As the symptoms of Alzheimer's disease progress slowly, it can be difficult to recognise that there's a problem. Many people feel that memory problems are simply a part of getting older. Also, the disease process itself may (but not always) prevent people recognising changes in their memory. But Alzheimer's disease is not a "normal" part of the ageing process. An accurate and timely diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease can give you the best chance to prepare and plan for the future, as well as receive any treatment or support that may help. If you're worried about your memory or think you may have dementia, it's a good idea to see a GP. If possible, someone who knows you well should be with you as they can help describe any changes or problems they have noticed. If you're worried about someone else, encourage them to make an appointment and perhaps suggest that you go along with them. There's no single test that can be used to diagnose Alzheimer's disease. And it's important to remember that memory problems do not necessarily mean you have Alzheimer's disease. A GP will ask questions about any problems you're experiencing and may do some tests to rule out other conditions. If Alzheimer's disease is suspected, you may be referred to a specialist service to: assess your symptoms in more detail organise further testing, such as brain scans if necessary create a treatment and care plan Read more about diagnosing Alzheimer's disease . How Alzheimer's disease is treated There's currently no cure for Alzheimer's disease, but medicines are available that can help relieve some of the symptoms. Various other types of support are also available to help people with Alzheimer's live as independently as possible, such as making changes to your home environment so it's easier to move around and remember daily tasks. Psychological treatments such as cognitive stimulation therapy may also be offered to help support your memory, problem solving skills and language ability. Read more about treating Alzheimer's disease . Outlook People with Alzheimer's disease can live for several years after they start to develop symptoms. But this can vary considerably from person to person. Alzheimer's disease is a life-limiting illness, although many people diagnosed with the condition will die from another cause. As Alzheimer's disease is a progressive neurological condition, it can cause problems with swallowing. This can lead to aspiration (food being inhaled into the lungs), which can cause frequent chest infections. It's also common for people with Alzheimer's disease to eventually have difficulty eating and have a reduced appetite. There's increasing awareness that people with Alzheimer's disease need palliative care . This includes support for families, as well as the person with Alzheimer's. Can Alzheimer's disease be prevented? As the exact cause of Alzheimer's disease is not clear, there's no known way to prevent the condition. But there are things you can do that may reduce your risk or delay the onset of dementia, such as: stopping smoking and cutting down on alcohol eating a healthy, balanced diet and maintaining a healthy weight staying physically fit and mentally active These measures have other health benefits, such as lowering your risk of cardiovascular disease and improving your overall mental health. Read more about preventing Alzheimer's disease . Dementia research There are dozens of dementia research projects going on around the world, many of which are based in the UK. If you have a diagnosis of dementia or are worried about memory problems, you can help scientists better understand the disease by taking part in research. If you're a carer for someone with dementia, you can also take part in research. You can sign up to take part in trials on the NHS Join Dementia Research website . More information Dementia can affect all aspects of a person's life, as well as their family's. If you have been diagnosed with dementia, or you're caring for someone with the condition, remember that advice and support is available to help you live well. Read more about: Staying independent with dementia Living well with dementia Communicating with someone with dementia Looking after someone with dementia Coping with dementia behaviour changes Help and support for people with dementia Dementia, social services and the NHS Information: Social care and support guide If you: need help with day-to-day living because of illness or disability care for someone regularly because they're ill, elderly or disabled – including family members Our guide to care and support explains your options and where you can get support. Page last reviewed: 04 July 2024 Next review due: 04 July 2027 Next : Symptoms</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>A lazy eye (amblyopia) is when the vision in 1 eye does not develop properly. Rarely, both eyes can be affected. Symptoms of a lazy eye A lazy eye does not always cause symptoms and is often first diagnosed during an eye test. The main symptoms include: shutting 1 eye or squinting when looking at things eyes pointing in different directions (a squint ) not being able to follow an object or person with your eyes tilting your head when looking at something having tired eyes and rubbing your eyes a lot headaches difficulty catching or throwing tripping or falling over a lot blinking a lot Many children do not notice anything wrong with their vision. You can check a younger child's eyes by covering each eye with your hand, 1 at a time. They may complain if you cover their good eye. Older children may say they're not able to see as well with 1 eye and may have problems with reading, writing and drawing. Non-urgent advice: Go to an opticians if: you're worried about your or your child's vision you have not had an eye test for 2 years Find an NHS sight test What happens during an eye test To check if you or your child have a lazy eye, an eye test specialist called an optometrist will usually do an eye test. You'll be asked to look at lights or read letters while different lenses are placed in front of your eyes. To check the health of your eyes, you or your child may be given eye drops so the optometrist can see the back of your eye more clearly. If you or your child needs glasses, you'll be given a prescription. You can take this to any optician. Find out more about eye tests for children Information: NHS eye tests NHS eye tests are free for some people, including: children aged under 18, or under 19 and in full-time education people who have diabetes or glaucoma people on some benefits, including Universal Credit Find out more about free NHS eye tests Treatments for a lazy eye How lazy eye is treated depends on what's causing it. Treatment for a lazy eye aims to improve vision in the weaker eye. This may include: wearing glasses to correct your vision wearing an eye patch over the stronger eye for a few hours a day for several months – these are usually worn with glasses using eye drops to temporarily blur vision in the stronger eye Treatment should ideally start before the age of 7, when vision is still developing. If lazy eye is caused by cataracts or a drooping eyelid, you may need surgery. You may also need to have surgery if you have a squint. This will straighten the eyes and allow them to work together better, but does not improve your vision. Help with the cost of glasses and contact lenses Some people are entitled to a voucher to help towards the cost of glasses or contact lenses, including: children aged under 18, or under 19 and in full-time education if you're on some benefits, including Universal Credit If you do not have a voucher, you'll have to pay for glasses or contact lenses. Find out more about NHS optical vouchers Page last reviewed: 04 January 2023 Next review due: 04 January 2026</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Amyloidosis is a group of rare conditions where a protein called amyloid builds up in your body. It can affect organs such as your heart, kidneys, liver, nerves or digestive system. It cannot be cured, but there are treatments that may help with symptoms. Symptoms of amyloidosis Common symptoms of amyloidosis include: feeling very tired or weak losing weight without trying to shortness of breath swollen feet or legs bruising around your eyes Other symptoms depend on which parts of your body are affected, so you may not have all the symptoms. They can include: a fast or slow heartbeat or chest pain, if your heart is affected loss of appetite, feeling or being sick, diarrhoea or constipation, if your digestive system is affected frothy pee, if your kidneys are affected pain, numbness or tingling in your hands and feet, if your nerves are affected Important These symptoms can be caused by many different conditions. Having them does not definitely mean you have amyloidosis. But it's important to get them checked by a GP. Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you have symptoms of amyloidosis How you get amyloidosis There are several types of amyloidosis, with different causes. Causes of the main types of amyloidosis Type Cause AL amyloidosis A problem with your bone marrow. Sometimes linked with multiple myeloma , a type of bone marrow cancer. AA amyloidosis Long-term inflammatory conditions such as rheumatoid arthritis , Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis , or infectious diseases such as tuberculosis (TB) . Hereditary ATTR amyloidosis An inherited genetic condition. Wild-type ATTR amyloidosis Develops as you get older, usually affecting men over 75 years old. Beta-2 microglobulin amyloidosis Having long-term dialysis . Tests for amyloidosis If a GP thinks you may have amyloidosis they'll refer you to a specialist. You may be seen in a specialist amyloidosis treatment centre. Amyloidosis is often hard to diagnose because the symptoms vary and are similar to other conditions. You'll usually have tests such as: blood tests and urine tests tests such as an electrocardiogram (ECG) , echocardiogram or MRI scan , to check your heart and other organs a biopsy , where a small sample of cells is removed and tested to check for amyloid a type of scan called a SAP scan, to show where amyloid has built up in your body genetic testing to find out if you have a hereditary type of amyloidosis These tests will show what type of amyloidosis you have and how it's affecting you. Treatments for amyloidosis There's no cure for amyloidosis, but some types can be managed well through treatment to improve the symptoms. But for some people, amyloidosis eventually leads to organs such as your heart or kidneys no longer working properly. Your doctor will explain your treatment options and what to expect. If your amyloidosis is caused by another health condition, such as rheumatoid arthritis, treating the condition can improve your symptoms. Other treatments depend on what type of amyloidosis you have and what parts of your body are affected. Treatments may include: medicines to help with symptoms, such as painkillers, anti-sickness medicines, or medicines that reduce swelling (diuretics) medicines to reduce the amount of amyloid your body produces kidney dialysis , if your kidneys are not working properly a kidney transplant or liver transplant, if these organs are damaged Treatments for AL amyloidosis If you have AL amyloidosis, caused by a problem with your bone marrow, you may be offered: chemotherapy to destroy the blood cells in your bone marrow that cause the condition a stem cell or bone marrow transplant Recording information about you and your condition If you have amyloidosis, your care team will pass information on to the National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service (NCARDRS) . This helps scientists look for better ways to prevent and treat this condition. You can opt out of the register at any time. Information: More information Myeloma UK: AL amyloidosis ATTR Amyloidosis Patients Association Page last reviewed: 23 August 2023 Next review due: 23 August 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Anabolic steroids are prescription-only medicines that are sometimes taken without medical advice to increase muscle mass and improve athletic performance. If used in this way, they can cause serious side effects and addiction. Anabolic steroids are manufactured drugs that copy the effects of the male hormone testosterone. They have limited medical uses and are not the same as corticosteroids , a different type of steroid drug that's more commonly prescribed. Are anabolic steroids illegal? Anabolic steroids are class C drugs, which can only be issued by pharmacists with a prescription. It's legal to have anabolic steroids for personal use. They can also be imported or exported, as long as this is carried out in person. This means they can't be posted or delivered by a courier or freight service. However, it's illegal to possess, import or export anabolic steroids if it's believed you're supplying or selling them. This includes giving them to friends. The penalty is an unlimited fine, or even a prison sentence of up to 14 years. In professional sport, most organisations ban anabolic steroid use and test competitors for banned steroids. If you do test positive, you may be banned from competing professionally. Why people misuse anabolic steroids Anabolic steroids can be used as performance-enhancing drugs that increase muscle mass and decrease fat, as well as causing many undesirable effects. Some people take them regularly to improve their physical performance and build up their bodies. However, people of all ages have been known to misuse these drugs, including adolescent boys who suffer from body dysmorphic disorder . This is a mental health condition where a person spends a lot of time worrying about flaws in their appearance. These flaws are often unnoticeable to others. People who have body dysmorphic disorder may take anabolic steroids because they don't see themselves as being physically big enough or strong enough. Some people believe taking anabolic steroids will help them become fit and healthy. This isn't true: taking anabolic steroids is a dangerous drug habit. How anabolic steroids are taken Anabolic steroids are usually injected into a muscle or taken by mouth as tablets, but they also come as creams or gels that are applied to the skin. Many people who use anabolic steroids are aware of the dangers of taking them, and believe that by taking the drugs in certain ways they can avoid side effects. Or they may take additional medicines to try to counter the side effects. Users might: Take the drugs for a period of time and then stop for a rest period before starting again. This is known as "cycling". Take more than one type of anabolic steroid at a time, known as "stacking", which they believe makes the steroids work better. Do a combination of both stacking and cycling, known as "pyramiding", where they start off taking a low dose of one or more anabolic steroids, and then increase the dose over time up to a maximum dose. They then stop taking them for a rest period to give the body a break before starting the cycle again. But there is no evidence that any of these methods actually reduce side effects and harms from taking anabolic steroids. Users tend to exercise more when they're taking high doses to make the most of their improved performance during this time. Side effects of anabolic steroids Regularly taking anabolic steroids can lead to physical and psychological changes in both men and women, as well as potentially dangerous medical conditions. Physical effects Effects of anabolic steroids in men can include: reduced sperm count infertility shrunken testicles erectile dysfunction hair loss breast development increased risk of prostate cancer severe acne stomach pain In women, anabolic steroids can cause: facial hair growth and body hair loss of breasts swelling of the clitoris a deepened voice an increased sex drive problems with periods hair loss severe acne In addition, both men and women who take anabolic steroids can develop any of the following medical conditions: heart attack or stroke liver or kidney problems or failure high blood pressure (hypertension) blood clots fluid retention high cholesterol Psychological effects Misusing anabolic steroids can also cause the following psychological or emotional effects: aggressive behaviour mood swings paranoia manic behaviour hallucinations and delusions Stunted growth in adolescents Anabolic steroids accelerate bone growth, so if they're misused by adolescents who haven't yet had the growth spurt associated with puberty, the drugs can cause premature ageing of the bones and restricted growth. Sharing needles As anabolic steroids are often injected, there are risks associated with sharing needles. These are the same risks associated with recreational drug use, and include: damage to veins, leading to ulcers or gangrene hepatitis B infection hepatitis C infection HIV transmission Addiction Anabolic steroids are addictive. This means you can crave the drug, require more to get the same effect, and have withdrawal symptoms if you suddenly stop taking it. A person who is addicted to anabolic steroids will want to keep using them despite experiencing unpleasant physical side effects. When doctors prescribe steroid medication, they always advise coming off the medication slowly by gradually reducing the dose. Coming off anabolic steroids suddenly can result in withdrawal symptoms that include: depression and apathy feelings of anxiety difficulty concentrating insomnia anorexia decreased sex drive extreme tiredness (fatigue) headaches muscle and joint pain Getting help You should see a GP if you think you're addicted to anabolic steroids. Treatment for an addiction to anabolic steroids will be similar to that of other types of addiction. The GP may refer you to a specially trained drugs counsellor. They'll discuss your addiction with you, how to safely stop taking steroids, and any obstacles you may face when trying to stop, plus tips for dealing with those obstacles. Further information and advice: Drug addiction: getting help Find drug addiction support services Help and advice on the FRANK website Page last reviewed: 13 April 2022 Next review due: 13 April 2025</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of iron deficiency anaemia Symptoms of iron deficiency anaemia can include: tiredness and lack of energy shortness of breath noticeable heartbeats (heart palpitations) paler than usual skin headaches Less common symptoms of iron deficiency anaemia Less common symptoms of iron deficiency anaemia (that are not usually connected to pregnancy) include: hearing ringing, buzzing or hissing noises inside your head (tinnitus) food tasting strange feeling itchy a sore tongue hair loss – you notice more hair coming out when brushing or washing it wanting to eat non-food items, such as paper or ice (pica) finding it hard to swallow (dysphagia) painful open sores (ulcers) in the corners of your mouth nail changes, such as spoon-shaped nails restless legs syndrome Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you think you might have iron deficiency anaemia What happens at your appointment To check if you have iron deficiency anaemia, your GP will ask you about your lifestyle and medical history. The GP will usually do a blood test to find out if the number of red blood cells you have is normal. This is called a full blood count (FBC) test, which also looks at other types of cells in your blood. You do not need to do anything to prepare for this test. Information: Iron deficiency anaemia is the most common type of anaemia. There are other types of anaemia, like vitamin B12 or folate deficiency anaemia , that the blood test will also check for. If the reason for the anaemia is not clear, the GP may do other tests to find out what might be causing your symptoms. This might include having a faecal immunochemical test (FIT) to look for blood in a sample of your poo. They might also refer you to a specialist for further checks. Treatment for iron deficiency anaemia Once the reason you have iron deficiency anaemia has been found (for example, an ulcer or heavy periods) the GP will recommend treatment. If the blood test shows your red blood cell count is low, iron tablets will be recommended to replace the iron that's missing from your body. You'll need to take them for about 6 months. Drinking orange juice after you've taken a tablet may help your body absorb the iron. Follow the GP's advice about how to take iron tablets. Some people get side effects when taking iron tablets like: constipation or diarrhoea tummy pain heartburn feeling sick darker than usual poo Try taking the tablets with or soon after food to reduce the chance of side effects. It's important to keep taking the tablets, even if you get side effects. Your GP may carry out repeat blood tests over the next few months to check that your iron level is getting back to normal. Important Keep iron supplement tablets out of the reach of children. An overdose of iron in a young child can be fatal. Things you can do to help with iron deficiency anaemia If your diet is partly causing your iron deficiency anaemia, your GP will tell you what foods are rich in iron so you can eat more of them. Eat more: dark-green leafy vegetables like watercress and curly kale cereals and bread with extra iron in them (fortified) meat dried fruit like apricots, prunes and raisins pulses (beans, peas and lentils) Eat and drink less: tea coffee milk and dairy foods with high levels of phytic acid, such as wholegrain cereals, which can stop your body absorbing iron from other foods and tablets Large amounts of these foods and drinks make it harder for your body to absorb iron. You might be referred to a specialist dietitian if you're finding it hard to include iron in your diet. Causes of iron deficiency anaemia Heavy periods and pregnancy are very common causes of iron deficiency anaemia. Heavy periods can be treated with medicine. In pregnancy, iron deficiency anaemia is most often caused by a lack of iron in your diet. Bleeding in the stomach and intestines is another common cause of iron deficiency anaemia. This can be caused by: taking non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) , such as ibuprofen and aspirin stomach ulcers inflammation of the bowel or food pipe (oesophagus) piles cancers of the bowel or stomach (but this is less common) Any other conditions or actions that cause blood loss could also lead to iron deficiency anaemia. If iron deficiency anaemia is not treated Untreated iron deficiency anaemia: can make you more at risk of illness and infection – a lack of iron affects the immune system may increase your risk of developing complications that affect the heart or lungs – such as an abnormally fast heartbeat (tachycardia) or heart failure can cause a greater risk of complications before and after birth if you're pregnant Page last reviewed: 26 January 2024 Next review due: 26 January 2027</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Vitamin B12 or B9 (commonly called folate) deficiency anaemia occurs when a lack of vitamin B12 or folate causes the body to produce abnormally large red blood cells that cannot function properly. Red blood cells carry oxygen around the body using a substance called haemoglobin. Anaemia is the general term for having either fewer red blood cells than normal or having an abnormally low amount of haemoglobin in each red blood cell. Symptoms of vitamin B12 or folate deficiency Vitamin B12 and folate perform several important functions in the body, including keeping the nervous system healthy. A deficiency in either of these vitamins can cause a wide range of problems, including: extreme tiredness a lack of energy pins and needles a sore and red tongue mouth ulcers muscle weakness problems with your vision psychological problems, which can range from mild depression or anxiety to confusion and dementia problems with memory, understanding and judgement Some of these problems can also happen if you have a deficiency in vitamin B12 or folate but do not have anaemia. When to see a GP See a GP if you think you may have a vitamin B12 or folate deficiency. These conditions can often be diagnosed based on your symptoms and the results of a blood test. It's important for vitamin B12 or folate deficiency anaemia to be diagnosed and treated as soon as possible. This is because although many of the symptoms improve with treatment, some problems caused by the condition can be irreversible. Causes of a vitamin B12 or folate deficiency There are a number of problems that can lead to a vitamin B12 or folate deficiency. These include: pernicious anaemia – where your immune system attacks healthy cells in your stomach, preventing your body absorbing vitamin B12 from the food you eat; this is the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency in the UK a lack of these vitamins in your diet – this is uncommon, but can happen if you have a vegan diet and do not take vitamin B12 supplements or eat foods fortified with vitamin B12 , follow a restrictive diet or have a generally poor diet for a long time medicine – certain medicines, including anticonvulsants and proton pump inhibitors (PPIs), can affect how much of these vitamins your body absorbs Both vitamin B12 deficiency and folate deficiency are more common in older people, affecting around 1 in 10 people aged 75 or over and 1 in 20 people aged 65 to 74. Treating vitamin B12 or folate deficiency anaemia Most cases of vitamin B12 and folate deficiency can be easily treated with injections or tablets to replace the missing vitamins. Vitamin B12 supplements are usually given by injection at first. Then, depending on whether your B12 deficiency is related to your diet, you'll either require B12 tablets between meals or regular injections. Treatments may last until your vitamin B12 levels have improved or you may need treatment for the rest of your life. Folic acid tablets are used to restore folate levels. These usually need to be taken for 4 months. In some cases, improving your diet can help treat the condition and prevent it coming back. Vitamin B12 is found in meat, fish, eggs, dairy products and specially fortified foods. Good sources of folate include green vegetables, such as broccoli, brussels sprouts and peas. Complications of vitamin B12 or folate deficiency anaemia Although it's uncommon, vitamin B12 or folate deficiency (with or without anaemia) can lead to complications , particularly if you have been deficient in vitamin B12 or folate for some time. Potential complications can include: problems with the nervous system temporary infertility heart conditions pregnancy complications and birth defects Adults with severe anaemia are also at risk of developing heart failure. Some complications improve with appropriate treatment, but others, such as problems with the nervous system, can sometimes be permanent. Page last reviewed: 20 February 2023 Next review due: 20 February 2026 Next : Symptoms</text><label>1</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of an anal fissure The main symptoms of an anal fissure are: severe, sharp pain when you poo burning pain after you poo that may last for several hours bright red blood in the toilet or on the toilet paper after you poo There are other causes of pain around your anus and bleeding from the bottom (rectal bleeding) , such as piles (haemorrhoids) . How you can treat or prevent an anal fissure yourself If you think you might have an anal fissure, there are some things you can try to see if they help. Do take paracetamol or ibuprofen to help with pain drink lots of fluids and eat plenty of fibre to keep your poo soft have a warm, shallow bath after you poo to ease pain in your bottom keep your bottom clean and dry Don’t do not ignore the urge to poo Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: you or your child have symptoms of an anal fissure and they're getting worse, or there's no improvement after 7 days of treating it yourself What happens at your GP appointment To check if you have an anal fissure, your GP will ask about your symptoms and look at your anus. You may be referred to a specialist for an examination under general anaesthetic if: your GP is not sure if you have an anal fissure or if something serious may be causing it the examination is causing you pain or painful muscle movements in your anus (spasms) Treatments for an anal fissure An anal fissure usually heals on its own. If an anal fissure is not healing or your symptoms are getting worse, you may need treatment. The main treatments for anal fissures are: laxatives to help you poo if you have constipation medicines to help with pain after you poo, such as Buscopan or mebeverine a cream you put on your anus that helps with healing – you may need to use this for up to 8 weeks If these treatments do not work or you keep getting anal fissures, a procedure may be recommended, such as: an injection into your anus to help the muscles relax so the tear can heal making a small cut in the muscle in the anus to reduce tension and let the tear heal These will be done under general anaesthetic , so you'll be asleep and will not feel anything. Causes of anal fissures It's not always clear what causes an anal fissure. They're more common in people aged 15 to 40, and in young children. You may be more likely to get an anal fissure if you: have constipation – this is a common cause of anal fissures in children have diarrhoea a lot are pregnant or have given birth vaginally have a condition such as inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) , Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis have a sexually transmitted infection (STI) , such as syphilis or herpes Page last reviewed: 26 June 2025 Next review due: 26 June 2028</text><label>2</label></item><item><text>An anal fistula is a small tunnel that develops between the end of the bowel and the skin near the opening of the bottom (anus). It’s usually caused by an infection near the anus, which results in a collection of pus (abscess) in the nearby tissue. When the pus drains away, it can leave a small channel behind. Anal fistulas can cause unpleasant symptoms, such as discomfort and skin irritation, and will not usually get better on their own. Surgery is recommended in most cases. Symptoms of an anal fistula Symptoms of an anal fistula include: skin irritation around the anus a constant, throbbing pain that may be worse when you sit down, move around, poo or cough smelly discharge from near your anus passing pus or blood when you poo swelling and redness around your anus and a high temperature if you also have an abscess difficulty controlling bowel movements ( bowel incontinence ) in some cases The end of the fistula might be visible as a hole in the skin near your anus, although this may be difficult for you to see yourself. When to get medical advice See a GP if you have persistent symptoms of an anal fistula. They'll ask about your symptoms and whether you have any bowel conditions. They may also ask to examine your anus and gently insert a finger inside it ( rectal examination ) to check for signs of a fistula. If the GP thinks you might have a fistula, they can refer you to a specialist called a colorectal surgeon for further tests to confirm the diagnosis and determine the most suitable treatment. Tests you may have include: a further physical and rectal examination a proctoscopy, where a special telescope with a light on the end is used to look inside your anus an ultrasound scan , MRI scan or CT scan When to get medical help The GP will look at the skin around the opening of your bottom (anus) to check for signs of an anal fistula. They may also ask you if they can do a rectal examination . This involves gently inserting a gloved finger into your bottom. If the GP thinks you have an anal fistula, you may be referred to a specialist for further tests. Tests you may have include: using a thin tube with a light at one end to look inside your bottom – this procedure is called a proctoscopy scans, such as an ultrasound scan , CT scan or MRI scan Causes of anal fistulas Most anal fistulas develop after an anal abscess. You can get one if the abscess does not heal properly after the pus has drained away. Less common causes of anal fistulas include: Crohn's disease – a long-term condition where the digestive system becomes inflamed diverticulitis – infection of the small pouches that can stick out of the side of the large intestine (colon) hidradenitis suppurativa – a long-term skin condition that causes abscesses and scarring infection with tuberculosis (TB) or HIV a complication of surgery near the anus Treatments for an anal fistula Anal fistulas usually require surgery as they rarely heal if left untreated. The main options include: a fistulotomy – a procedure that involves cutting open the whole length of the fistula so it heals into a flat scar seton procedures – where a piece of surgical thread called a seton is placed in the fistula and left there for several weeks to help it heal before a further procedure is carried out to treat it All the procedures have different benefits and risks. You can discuss this with the surgeon. Many people do not need to stay in hospital overnight after surgery, although some may need to stay in hospital for a few days. Find out more about treating an anal fistula Page last reviewed: 21 February 2023 Next review due: 21 February 2026 Next : Treatment</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Anaphylaxis is a life-threatening allergic reaction that happens very quickly. It can be caused by food, medicine or insect stings. Call 999 if you think you or someone else is having an anaphylactic reaction. Symptoms of anaphylaxis Symptoms of anaphylaxis happen very quickly. They usually start within minutes of coming into contact with something you're allergic to, such as a food, medicine or insect sting. Symptoms include: swelling of your throat and tongue difficulty breathing or breathing very fast difficulty swallowing, tightness in your throat or a hoarse voice wheezing, coughing or noisy breathing feeling tired or confused feeling faint, dizzy or fainting skin that feels cold to the touch blue, grey or pale skin, lips or tongue – if you have brown or black skin, this may be easier to see on the palms of your hands or soles of your feet You may also have a rash that's swollen, raised or itchy. Immediate action required: Call 999 if: your lips, mouth, throat or tongue suddenly become swollen you're breathing very fast or struggling to breathe (you may become very wheezy or feel like you're choking or gasping for air) your throat feels tight or you're struggling to swallow your skin, tongue or lips turn blue, grey or pale (if you have black or brown skin, this may be easier to see on the palms of your hands or soles of your feet) you suddenly become very confused, drowsy or dizzy someone faints and cannot be woken up a child is limp, floppy or not responding like they normally do (their head may fall to the side, backwards or forwards, or they may find it difficult to lift their head or focus on your face) You or the person who's unwell may also have a rash that's swollen, raised or itchy. These can be signs of a serious allergic reaction and may need immediate treatment in hospital. What to do if you have anaphylaxis Follow these steps if you think you or someone you're with is having an anaphylactic reaction: Use an adrenaline auto-injector (such as an EpiPen) if you have one – instructions are included on the side of the injector. Call 999 for an ambulance and say that you think you're having an anaphylactic reaction. Lie down – you can raise your legs, and if you're struggling to breathe, raise your shoulders or sit up slowly (if you're pregnant, lie on your left side). If you have been stung by an insect, try to remove the sting if it's still in the skin. If your symptoms have not improved after 5 minutes, use a 2nd adrenaline auto-injector. Do not stand or walk at any time, even if you feel better. Information: How to use an adrenaline auto-injector There are different types of adrenaline auto-injectors and each one is given differently. EpiPen instructions (EpiPen website) Jext instructions (Jext website) Treatment for anaphylaxis Anaphylaxis needs to be treated in hospital immediately. Treatments can include: adrenaline given by an injection or drip in your vein oxygen fluids given by a drip in your vein You'll usually stay in hospital for around 2 to 12 hours, but you may need to stay longer. Before you leave hospital, you'll be given 2 adrenaline auto-injectors to keep in case you have another anaphylactic reaction. An adrenaline auto-injector is a special device for injecting adrenaline yourself. You'll be told how and when to use it. You should be shown how to use your adrenaline auto-injector each time you're prescribed it. You may also be referred to an allergy specialist for tests and advice. Things you can do to help prevent anaphylaxis There are some things you can do to help prevent anaphylaxis or prepare for if it happens. Do avoid the food, medicine or thing that you're allergic to – for example, if you have a food allergy, check food labels carefully and tell staff at restaurants and cafes about your allergy carry 2 adrenaline auto-injectors with you at all times check your adrenaline auto-injector expiry dates regularly and get new ones before they expire practise how to use your adrenaline auto-injector by using a trainer injector (an injector that has no needle or medicine in it) – you can order one online from the company that makes your injector teach friends, family, colleagues or carers how and when to use your adrenaline auto-injector use your adrenaline auto-injector if you think you may have anaphylaxis, even if your symptoms are mild wear medical alert jewellery such as a bracelet with information about your allergy – this tells other people about your allergy in case of an emergency Don’t do not leave your adrenaline auto-injectors anywhere too hot or cold such as in the fridge or outside in the sun Information: More information There's more advice about what you can do to avoid common allergies. Find out more about: food allergy insect bites and stings medicine allergy (Allergy UK website) latex allergy (Allergy UK website) Causes of anaphylaxis Anaphylaxis happens when your body has a serious reaction to something you're allergic to. Allergies that can sometimes cause anaphylaxis include: foods such as nuts, cows' milk, eggs, fish or sesame seeds medicines such as antibiotics or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) insect stings, such as wasp and bee stings anaesthetics latex (a type of rubber found in some rubber gloves and condoms) Sometimes it's not known what caused an anaphylactic reaction. Page last reviewed: 21 June 2023 Next review due: 21 June 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of a brain aneurysm Most brain aneurysms are small and do not cause symptoms. They're often found during a test for another condition. If you have a larger aneurysm, you may get symptoms such as: a headache pain above or around your eye changes in your vision, such as double vision dizziness and balance problems numbness or weakness on 1 side of your face difficulty concentrating and speaking problems with your short-term memory If a brain aneurysm bursts, it can cause a bleed on your brain called a subarachnoid haemorrhage . The main symptom is a sudden, severe headache that's sometimes described as a "thunderclap headache". Immediate action required: Call 999 if: You or someone else suddenly get: a headache that's extremely painful and does not go away weakness in the face – 1 side of the face may droop (fall) and it might be hard to smile weakness or numbness in 1 arm or down 1 side of the body – it may not be possible to lift both arms fully and keep them there speech problems, such as slurring words, sounding confused, or finding it difficult to speak or find the right words blurred vision or loss of sight in 1 or both eyes Information: Do not drive yourself to A&amp;E. The person you speak to at 999 will give you advice about what to do. Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: you keep getting headaches, they do not go away or they're getting worse you have pain above or around your eye you have any other symptoms of a brain aneurysm that do not go away You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Treatment for a brain aneurysm Treatment is not usually needed for small brain aneurysms that are not causing symptoms. This is because they often do not get bigger and have a low risk of bursting. You may just need regular follow-up scans to check if it’s getting bigger. Brain aneurysm surgery If there’s a risk of the aneurysm bursting, or if it’s already burst, surgery will usually be needed. The 2 main types of surgery are: surgical clipping – where a small metal clip is attached to the blood vessel in the brain to stop blood flowing into the aneurysm endovascular surgery – where a coil or small piece of wire mesh is put inside the aneurysm to slow the flow of blood into it and help a blood clot to form If possible, your surgeon will talk to you about the procedure they feel is most suitable for you and discuss any risks involved. General anaesthetic is used for both surgical clipping and endovascular surgery, so you’ll be asleep and unable to feel any pain or discomfort during the procedure. Information: Find out more Headway: brain aneurysms and how they are treated Causes of a brain aneurysm It's not always clear what causes brain aneurysms. But things that increase your chances of getting a brain aneurysm include: smoking high blood pressure having a close relative who has had a brain aneurysm an injury to a blood vessel in your brain taking drugs, such as cocaine having certain genetic conditions, such as autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome Things you can do to help if you have a brain aneurysm If you have a brain aneurysm there are some things you can do to reduce the risk of it getting bigger and bursting. Do stop smoking if you smoke keep your blood pressure at a healthy level – you can get your blood pressure checked at a pharmacy or GP surgery make healthy lifestyle changes, such as eating a balanced diet , exercising regularly and losing weight if you’re overweight Don’t do not drink too much alcohol do not take illegal drugs Important: Driving You may not be allowed to drive if you have a brain aneurysm. Your doctor will be able to advise you about whether it’s safe for you to drive and if you need to tell the DVLA. Information: Find out more NHS help to get healthy (Better Health) How to lower your blood pressure (British Heart Foundation) Help and support for a brain aneurysm Finding out you have a brain aneurysm can be scary and worrying. As well as getting help and advice from your doctor, you may find it helpful to talk to other people with the condition, either at a local support group or online. Headway Information, help and support for anyone affected by brain injury. Website: www.headway.org.uk/ Helpline: 0808 800 2244 Headway: online communities Brain and Spine Foundation Information and support for anyone affected by brain conditions, including brain aneurysm. Website: www.brainandspine.org.uk Helpline: 0808 808 1000 Brain and Spine Foundation: join a support group Page last reviewed: 09 October 2025 Next review due: 09 October 2028</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Angelman syndrome is a rare genetic condition that affects the nervous system and causes severe physical and learning disabilities. A person with Angelman syndrome will have a near-normal life expectancy, but they will need support throughout their life. Characteristics of Angelman syndrome A child with Angelman syndrome will begin to show signs of delayed development at around 6 to 12 months of age, such as being unable to sit unsupported or make babbling noises. Later, they may not speak at all or may only be able to say a few words. However, most children with Angelman syndrome will be able to communicate using gestures, signs or other systems. The movement of a child with Angelman syndrome will also be affected. They may have difficulty walking because of issues with balance and co-ordination ( ataxia ). Their arms may tremble or make jerky movements, and their legs may be stiff. Several distinctive behaviours are associated with Angelman syndrome, although a child with the condition may not have all of these behaviours. They include: frequent laughter and smiling, often with little stimulus being easily excitable, often flapping the hands being restless (hyperactive) having a short attention span trouble sleeping and needing less sleep than other children a particular fascination with water By around 2 years of age, a small head which may also be flat at the back (microbrachycephaly) may be noticeable in some children with Angelman syndrome. Children with Angelman syndrome may also start to have seizures or fits around this age. Other possible features of the syndrome include: tendency to stick the tongue out crossed eyes (strabismus) skin, hair and eyes that are paler than other family members a wide mouth with widely spaced teeth a side-to-side curvature of the spine ( scoliosis ) walking with arms in the air Some young babies with Angelman syndrome may have difficulties feeding because they're unable to co-ordinate sucking and swallowing. In such cases, they may need to be fed through a feeding tube. Babies with Angelman syndrome may need to be treated for reflux. Causes of Angelman syndrome In most cases of Angelman syndrome, the child's parents do not have the condition and the genetic difference responsible for the syndrome happens by chance around the time of conception. Angelman syndrome usually happens when the gene known as UBE3A is either missing or not working properly. A gene is a single unit of genetic material (DNA) that acts as an instruction for the way an individual is made and develops. Usually a child gets 2 copies of this gene, one from each parent, but only the gene from the mother is active. Most cases of Angelman syndrome are caused by the child not getting a copy of the UBE3A gene from its mother, or the gene not working. This means there's no active copy of the gene in the child's brain. In a small number of cases, Angelman syndrome happens when a child gets 2 inactive copies of the gene from their father, rather than 1 from each parent. Sometimes the cause of Angelman syndrome is unknown. Most children in these unexplained cases have different conditions involving other genes or chromosomes. Diagnosing Angelman syndrome Angelman syndrome may be suspected if a child's development is delayed and they have the syndrome's distinctive characteristics. A blood test is used to confirm the diagnosis. Several genetic tests will be done on the blood sample. These tests look for: any chromosomes or pieces of chromosomes that are missing changes in the mother's or father's UBE3A gene that they may have passed on changes in the child's UBE3A gene that would stop it from working For each child with Angelman syndrome, it's important to know the genetic change that caused the condition. This helps to determine your chance of having another child with Angelman syndrome. Most children with Angelman syndrome are diagnosed between the ages of 9 months to 6 years, when physical and behavioural symptoms become apparent. If your child is diagnosed with Angelman syndrome, you will be able to talk to a genetic doctor about what support they might need. Managing Angelman syndrome Your child may benefit from some of the following treatments and aids: anti-epileptic medicine to control seizures physiotherapy may improve posture, balance and walking ability; it's also important to prevent permanent stiffening of the joints as people with Angelman syndrome get older communication therapy may help them develop non-verbal language skills, such as sign language and using visual aids, or ways to help them communicate such as Signalong , Makaton or PECS ; using iPad applications and similar tablet devices may also help behavioural therapy may be recommended to help overcome behaviours you find hard to manage, such as hyperactivity and a short attention span In later childhood, the seizures usually improve, although they may return in adulthood. With age, people with Angelman syndrome become less hyperactive and may sleep better. Most people with the syndrome will have learning disability and limited speech throughout their life. In adults, some mobility may be lost and joints may stiffen. People with Angelman syndrome usually have good general health and are often able to improve their communication and acquire new skills. While there's currently no cure for Angelman syndrome, research into treatments is being done in other countries. There are also clinical trials looking at treatment for some of the symptoms associated with Angelman syndrome, such as seizures. Find out more about: how to care for a disabled child support and benefits for carers Help and support AngelmanUK is a charity providing information and support for parents and carers of people with Angelman syndrome. You can call their helpline (0300 999 0102) to speak with parents of people with Angelman syndrome, who can offer you advice and support. The Foundation for Angelman Syndrome Therapeutics (FAST) is a charity that provides information about Angelman syndrome. The website includes a section for parents who have a child who has recently been diagnosed with Angelman syndrome. National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service If your child has Angelman syndrome, your clinical team will pass information about them on to the National Congenital Anomaly and Rare Disease Registration Service (NCARDRS) . The NCARDRS helps scientists look for better ways to prevent and treat this condition. You can opt out of the register at any time. Page last reviewed: 09 March 2023 Next review due: 09 March 2026</text><label>3</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of angina The main symptom of angina is sudden pain in your chest, neck, shoulders, jaw or arms. The pain may: feel like tightness, squeezing or pressure, or like a dull ache make you feel sick, breathless, dizzy or sweaty These symptoms may be called an angina attack, episode or pain. They are often brought on by exercise, stress, emotion or cold temperatures – although sometimes there's no obvious trigger. Angina attacks usually last less than 10 minutes and should stop after resting for a few minutes or taking your angina medicine. How to treat an angina attack If you've been diagnosed with angina and get chest pain, follow the instructions you've been given for treating your angina: Stop what you're doing and rest. Use any medicine you've been prescribed – this is usually glyceryl trinitrate (GTN). Take another dose after 5 minutes if the first dose does not help. If you still have symptoms 5 minutes after taking the 2nd dose, call 999 for an ambulance. Immediate action required: Call 999 now if: you've been diagnosed with angina and have chest pain that does not stop after resting for a few minutes or after taking your angina medicine you get sudden pain or discomfort in your chest that does not go away – the pain can feel like squeezing or pressure inside your chest, burning or indigestion you get pain that spreads to your left or right arm, or your neck, jaw, shoulder, stomach or back you have chest pain and you feel sweaty, sick, light-headed or short of breath You could be having a heart attack. Call 999 straight away as you need immediate treatment in hospital. Information: Do not drive yourself to A&amp;E. The person you speak to at 999 will give you advice about what to do. Urgent advice: Get help from NHS 111 if: you have chest pain or other symptoms of angina that come and go you've been diagnosed with angina and it feels worse than before, is happening more often, lasts longer or happens when you're resting You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . What happens at your GP appointment If a GP thinks you may have angina, you'll be referred to a heart specialist (cardiologist). You may have tests including: blood tests an electrocardiogram (ECG) to check the electrical activity of your heart checking the level of oxygen in your blood scans, such as an angiogram , MRI scan or CT scan Causes of angina Angina happens when the heart does not get enough blood. This is usually due to coronary heart disease , where the blood vessels supplying blood to the heart become narrowed or blocked by fatty deposits. But it can also be caused by the blood vessels in your heart tightening when they should not (vasospastic angina or microvascular angina). You're more likely to get angina if you: are a man aged 45 or over, or a woman aged 55 or over smoke drink more than 14 units of alcohol a week are living with obesity or overweight have high blood pressure or high cholesterol have had heart problems before, like a heart attack or heart rhythm problem (arrhythmia) have close relatives who have heart problems have another condition, such as diabetes, arthritis or kidney disease Information: British Heart Foundation has more information about vasospastic angina and microvascular angina . Treatment for angina If you have angina, you may be given medicine to: treat an angina attack if you have one ( glyceryl trinitrate ) lower your chances of having an angina attack, such as beta blockers reduce your risk of having a stroke or heart attack, such as low-dose aspirin or statins Sometimes you may be recommended to have surgery to increase the blood flow to your heart ( coronary angioplasty or a coronary artery bypass ). Things you can do to help prevent angina attacks If you have angina, there are things you can do to help symptoms or reduce the chance of attacks. Do avoid things that trigger your angina attacks as much as possible, like stress, cold temperatures or eating large meals always have your angina medicine with you – use it as you have been told by your doctor try to quit smoking, if you smoke try to keep to a healthy weight eat a balanced diet have the most active lifestyle your symptoms will allow try to cut down on alcohol if you drink more than 14 units a week Information: NHS help to get healthy NHS Better Health has free tools and support to help you lose weight, quit smoking, drink less and get active. Visit the NHS Better Health website How angina affects your life Having angina means you're at higher risk of having a heart attack or stroke. It's important to treat it and make healthy lifestyle changes to reduce this risk. With treatment, the symptoms should improve over time and may eventually stop. If your symptoms are well controlled, angina will not usually have a big impact on your life. You'll usually be able to continue with most things, including exercise and sex. But angina may affect your work if you have a job that involves a lot of physical activity, or if you drive buses, coaches or lorries. Your doctor will talk to you about any changes you may need to make, and whether you need to inform the DVLA about your condition. It's also best to speak to your doctor before you take up a new activity or if you're worried about exercising. You may also need to think about practical things like always carrying your angina medicine, having spare medicine available and making sure you have enough with you when travelling. Information: More information British Heart Foundation: understanding angina booklet British Heart Foundation: support with everyday life Video: Angina In this video an expert describes the symptoms, stages and treatment of angina. Media last reviewed: 12 November 2024 Media review due: 12 November 2027 Page last reviewed: 18 March 2025 Next review due: 18 March 2028</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Angioedema is sudden swelling that is often caused by an allergic reaction. It can be very serious if your throat becomes swollen and your breathing is affected. Treatment can help keep the swelling under control. Symptoms of angioedema Angioedema is where a part of the body suddenly becomes swollen. You'll usually have a raised, itchy rash ( hives ) if an allergic reaction has caused the swelling. Areas of the body commonly affected include: the face – particularly the lips, tongue and eyelids the hands or feet the genitals Sometimes the bowel may also become swollen, which can cause stomach pain. Less commonly, the throat can swell up, leading to breathing difficulties. This is a medical emergency and immediate treatment is needed. Immediate action required: Call 999 if: your lips, mouth, throat or tongue suddenly become swollen you're breathing very fast or struggling to breathe (you may become very wheezy or feel like you're choking or gasping for air) your throat feels tight or you're struggling to swallow your skin, tongue or lips turn blue, grey or pale (if you have black or brown skin, this may be easier to see on the palms of your hands or soles of your feet) you suddenly become very confused, drowsy or dizzy someone faints and cannot be woken up a child is limp, floppy or not responding like they normally do (their head may fall to the side, backwards or forwards, or they may find it difficult to lift their head or focus on your face) You or the person who's unwell may also have a rash that's swollen, raised or itchy. These can be signs of a serious allergic reaction and may need immediate treatment in hospital. Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: part of your body suddenly becomes swollen (such as your hands, feet or genitals) You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Treatments for angioedema You may not need treatment for angioedema if the swelling is mild or it only affects a small area of your body. If the swelling is severe or widespread, or if it affects your lips, tongue, or throat, you'll usually need emergency treatment in hospital. Treatments for angioedema include: identifying and avoiding the underlying cause – if a medicine is thought to be the cause, you may be given a different one to take instead antihistamine medicine, such as cetirizine , fexofenadine or loratadine steroid tablets, such as prednisolone If you have a type of angioedema that keeps coming back (hereditary angioedema), you may also need medicine to stop this happening. You may have regular reviews to check if your treatment is working. If your symptoms do not improve or get worse, you may need to go back to hospital for further tests and treatment. Types of angioedema Types of angioedema Cause Type Angioedema caused by an allergic reaction to certain foods, medicines or substances Acute allergic angioedema A non-allergic reaction to a medicine, most commonly angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors Non-allergic angioedema Long-term angioedema where the cause is unknown Idiopathic angioedema A rare and potentially life-threatening type of angioedema that's often inherited from your parents Hereditary angioedema A very rare type of angioedema that you can get if you have lymphoma (cancer), or a condition that affects the connective tissue, such as lupus Acquired angioedema Page last reviewed: 18 January 2023 Next review due: 18 January 2026</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Information: This page is about human bites and bites from animals, such as cats and dogs, that have broken the skin. There's a separate page about snake bites . What to do after animal or human bites There are some things you can do after being bitten by an animal or a person. Do clean the wound with soap and warm water gently squeeze the wound so it bleeds slightly (unless it's already bleeding) – this can help reduce the risk of infection press a dry dressing or clean cloth firmly onto the wound to stop the bleeding if it's bleeding heavily after cleaning the wound, gently pat it dry and cover it with a clean dressing take paracetamol or ibuprofen to help ease any pain and swelling – children under 16 should not take aspirin Urgent advice: Get help from NHS 111 if: You've been bitten and: you think there may be objects like teeth, hair or dirt in the wound the bite is hot or swollen (it may also be painful, red or darker than the surrounding skin, which may be harder to see on black or brown skin) you have a high temperature, or feel hot, cold or shivery fluid is leaking from the bite the bite smells unpleasant you were bitten on your hands, feet, face or head you were bitten by a person you have not had a tetanus vaccine in the last 10 years You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Immediate action required: Go to A&amp;E if: You've been bitten by an animal or person and: the wound is large or deep you cannot stop the bleeding If a body part, such as part of a finger or ear has been torn off, wrap it in clean tissue and put it in a plastic bag. Put some ice around the bag and take it with you to hospital. Find your nearest A&amp;E Information: Do not drive to A&amp;E. Ask someone to drive you or call 999 and ask for an ambulance. Bring any medicines you take with you. Treatments for animal and human bites If you've been bitten by an animal or person, a doctor or nurse will check the wound. They may: clean the bite thoroughly – if the wound is very dirty, some of the affected area may need to be removed to reduce the risk of infection close the wound with stitches, sticky strips or special glue, or leave it open to heal give you antibiotics to stop the wound becoming infected check your risk of getting tetanus and rabies – you'll be given treatment to prevent these serious infections if needed If you've been bitten by a person, you may also be offered a blood test to check for hepatitis B , hepatitis C and HIV . Page last reviewed: 27 October 2025 Next review due: 27 October 2028</text><label>5</label></item><item><text>Swelling in the ankles, feet or legs often goes away on its own. See a GP if it does not get better in a few days. Common causes of swollen ankles, feet and legs Swelling in the ankles, feet and legs is often caused by a build-up of fluid in these areas, called oedema. Oedema is usually caused by: standing or sitting in the same position for too long eating too much salty food being overweight being pregnant taking certain medicines – such as some blood pressure medicines, contraceptive pills, hormone therapy, antidepressants or steroids Oedema can also be caused by: an injury – such as a strain or sprain an insect bite or sting problems with your kidneys, liver or heart a blood clot an infection Information: Find out more about swollen ankles, feet and fingers in pregnancy Symptoms of oedema Symptoms of oedema include: Swollen or puffy ankles, feet or legs. Credit: CaptureIt / Alamy Stock Photo Shiny or stretched skin. Credit: SCIENCE PHOTO LIBRARY Changes in skin colour, discomfort, stiffness and dents when you press on the skin. How to ease swelling yourself Swelling in your ankles, feet or legs should go away on its own, but there are some things you can try to help. Do raise your legs or the swollen area on a chair or pillows when you can get some gentle exercise, like walking, to improve your blood flow wear wide, comfortable shoes with a low heel and soft sole wash, dry and moisturise your feet to avoid infections Don’t do not stand or sit for long periods of time do not wear clothes, socks or shoes that are too tight Non-urgent advice: See a GP if: 1 or both of your ankles, foot or legs are swollen and: it has not improved after treating it at home for a few days it gets worse Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: you have swelling in 1 ankle, foot or leg and there's no obvious cause, such as an injury the swelling is severe, painful or starts very suddenly the swollen area is red or feels hot to the touch your temperature is very high, or you feel hot and shivery you have diabetes and your feet, ankles or legs are swollen You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Immediate action required: Call 999 if: you feel short of breath or are struggling to breathe your chest feels tight, heavy or painful you're coughing up blood You could have a blood clot in your lungs, which needs immediate treatment in hospital. Information: Do not drive yourself to A&amp;E. The person you speak to at 999 will give you advice about what to do. Treatment for swelling and oedema Treatment for swelling or oedema that does not go away on its own will depend on the cause. Your GP can help you with the right treatment. Speak to your GP about making, lifestyle changes, such as losing weight or going on a low-salt diet. Page last reviewed: 18 January 2022 Next review due: 18 January 2025</text><label>0</label></item><item><text>Ankylosing spondylitis (AS) is a long-term condition in which the spine and other areas of the body become inflamed. It's a type of axial spondyloarthritis. In AS changes to the spine can be seen on an X-ray. There is a similar condition called non-radiographic axial spondyloarthritis, where changes to the spine cannot be seen on an X-ray, but can sometimes be seen on an MRI scan. This information is about AS. The symptoms and treatment are similar if you have non-radiographic axial spondyloarthritis. AS and non-radiographic axial spondyloarthritis tend to first develop in teenagers and young adults. Symptoms of ankylosing spondylitis The symptoms of AS can vary, but usually involve: back pain and stiffness pain and swelling in other parts of the body – caused by inflammation of the joints ( arthritis ) and inflammation where a tendon joins a bone (enthesitis) extreme tiredness (fatigue) These symptoms tend to develop gradually, usually over several months or years, and may come and go over time. In some people the condition gets better with time, but for others it can get slowly worse. Read about symptoms of ankylosing spondylitis . When to seek medical advice You should see your GP if you have persistent symptoms of AS. If your GP thinks you may have the condition, they should refer you to a specialist in conditions affecting muscles and joints (rheumatologist) for further tests and any necessary treatment. Further tests may include blood tests and imaging tests. Read about diagnosing ankylosing spondylitis . Causes of ankylosing spondylitis It's not known what causes the condition, but there's thought to be a link with a particular gene variant known as HLA-B27. Read about the causes of ankylosing spondylitis . Treating ankylosing spondylitis There's no cure for AS and it's not possible to reverse the damage caused by the condition. However, treatment is available to relieve the symptoms and help delay its progression. In most cases treatment involves a combination of: exercises carried out individually or in groups to reduce pain and stiffness physiotherapy – where physical methods, such as massage and manipulation, are used to improve comfort and spinal flexibility medicine to help relieve pain and reduce inflammation – such as painkillers, anti-tumour necrosis factor (TNF) medication and other forms of biological therapy Surgery is sometimes needed to repair significantly damaged joints or correct severe bends in the spine, but this is uncommon. Read about treating ankylosing spondylitis . Complications of ankylosing spondylitis The outlook for AS is highly variable. For some people the condition improves after an initial period of inflammation, whereas for others it can get progressively worse over time. Some people with AS are able to remain fully independent or minimally disabled in the long term. However, some people eventually become severely disabled as a result of the bones in their spine fusing in a fixed position and damage to other joints, such as the hips or knees. With modern treatments, AS does not normally affect life expectancy significantly, although the condition is associated with an increased risk of other potentially life-threatening problems. For example, AS can lead to: weakening of the bones ( osteoporosis ) spinal fractures cardiovascular disease – a group of conditions affecting the heart and blood vessels Read about the complications of ankylosing spondylitis . Living with AS The National Axial Spondyloarthritis Society (NASS) has information on living with the condition, including advice on working, travelling and driving. Video: Back stretches In this video, a physiotherapist shows some simple back stretches to help prevent aches and pains. Media last reviewed: 16 November 2023 Media review due: 16 November 2026 See exercise video safety information The exercises in this series of videos are suitable for most people in good health with a reasonable level of fitness. Unless stated otherwise, they are general exercises only and are not aimed at treating any specific cause of pain or condition. Video titles and descriptions can give more information on how difficult the exercises are and who they are for. Get advice from a healthcare professional (such as a GP) before trying them if: you are not sure if the exercises are suitable for your current level of fitness you have a health problem, an injury, any symptoms, are feeling unwell, or you have had a recent health event such as a heart attack or operation you have any other concerns about your health you are pregnant or have recently given birth Stop the exercise immediately if you feel any pain or become unwell. If you are concerned about any symptoms, or they do not go away, get help from 111 online or call 111 for advice. Page last reviewed: 05 January 2023 Next review due: 05 January 2026 Next : Symptoms</text><label>1</label></item><item><text>Antiphospholipid syndrome (APS), sometimes known as Hughes syndrome, is a disorder of the immune system that causes an increased risk of blood clots. This means people with APS are at greater risk of developing conditions such as: DVT (deep vein thrombosis , a blood clot that usually develops in the leg arterial thrombosis (a clot in an artery), which can cause a stroke or heart attack blood clots in the brain, leading to problems with balance, mobility, vision, speech and memory Pregnant women with APS also have an increased risk of having a miscarriage , although the exact reasons for this are uncertain. APS doesn't always cause noticeable problems. Some people have general symptoms that can be similar to those of multiple sclerosis (a common condition affecting the central nervous system), such as tiredness or numbness and tingling in different parts of the body. Find out more about signs and symptoms of APS What causes antiphospholipid syndrome? APS is an autoimmune condition. This means the immune system, which usually protects the body from infection and illness, attacks healthy tissue by mistake. In APS, the immune system produces abnormal antibodies called antiphospholipid antibodies. These target proteins attached to fat molecules (phospholipids), which makes the blood more likely to clot. It's not known what causes the immune system to produce abnormal antibodies. As with other autoimmune conditions, genetic, hormonal and environmental factors are thought to play a part. Find out more about the causes of APS Who's affected APS can affect people of all ages, including children and babies. But most people are diagnosed with APS between 20 and 50 years of age, and it affects 3 to 5 times as many women as men. It's not clear how many people in the UK have the condition. Diagnosing APS Diagnosing APS can sometimes be difficult, as some of the symptoms are similar to multiple sclerosis. This means blood tests to identify the antibodies responsible for APS are essential in diagnosing the condition. Find out more about diagnosing APS How antiphospholipid syndrome is treated Although there's no cure for APS, the risk of developing blood clots can be greatly reduced if it's correctly diagnosed. An anticoagulant medicine , such as warfarin , or an antiplatelet, such as low-dose aspirin , is usually prescribed. These reduce the likelihood of unnecessary blood clots forming, but still allow clots to form when you cut yourself. Treatment with these medications can also improve a pregnant woman's chance of having a successful pregnancy. With treatment, it's estimated there's about an 80% chance of having a successful pregnancy. Most people respond well to treatment and can lead normal, healthy lives. But a small number of people with APS continue to experience blood clots despite extensive treatment. Find out more about treating APS Catastrophic antiphospholipid syndrome In very rare cases, blood clots can suddenly form throughout the body, resulting in multiple organ failure. This is known as catastrophic antiphospholipid syndrome (CAPS). CAPS requires immediate emergency treatment in hospital with high-dose anticoagulants . Read more about the complications of APS Further information APS Support UK is a UK-based charity for people living with antiphospholipid syndrome. The APS Support UK website has a range of information, resources and useful contacts. Page last reviewed: 20 June 2022 Next review due: 20 June 2025 Next : Symptoms</text><label>1</label></item><item><text>Symptoms of appendicitis Symptoms of appendicitis usually start with pain in the middle of your abdomen (tummy), around your belly button. After a few hours the pain usually moves to the lower right side of your abdomen, and gets worse. The pain may feel worse when you move, cough or press on the area. It may feel slightly better when you pull your knees up to your chest. Some people with appendicitis do not have the usual pain symptoms. For example, you might have pain that's less severe, develops more slowly, or in a different place. This can be more likely if you're pregnant and in young children and older people. Other symptoms of appendicitis can include: feeling or being sick, or loss of appetite a high temperature constipation or diarrhoea peeing more than usual sudden confusion (in older people) If appendicitis is not treated quickly, your appendix can burst. If this happens your pain may suddenly get better for a short time. You'll then usually have severe pain that spreads to the whole of your abdomen. It may be very painful to move. If you're not sure it's appendicitis Many other conditions can cause pain in your abdomen, including: urinary tract infections kidney stones or gallstones bowel problems such as irritable bowel syndrome or Crohn's disease conditions affecting your womb or ovaries, such as pelvic inflammatory disease or a ruptured ovarian cyst an ectopic pregnancy But do not try to diagnose the problem yourself. Get medical help if you're worried. Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: You or your child have pain in your abdomen (tummy) that: is gradually getting worse or does not go away moves to the lower right side of your abdomen You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Immediate action required: Call 999 or go to A&amp;E if: You or your child have: severe pain in your abdomen (tummy) confusion, blotchy or paler than usual skin (on brown or black skin this may be easier to see on the palms of the hands or soles of the feet) or difficulty breathing – these could be signs of sepsis Find your nearest A&amp;E Information: Do not drive to A&amp;E. Ask someone to drive you or call 999 and ask for an ambulance. Bring any medicines you take with you. How appendicitis is diagnosed If you have symptoms of appendicitis, a GP or hospital doctor will feel your abdomen (tummy) to check for pain and swelling. You'll need to go to hospital for tests and treatment. Tests you may have include: blood tests testing a sample of your pee scans such as an ultrasound scan or CT scan to check for swelling in your appendix a pregnancy test if there's a chance you could be pregnant There's no test that can always show if you have appendicitis. It can be hard to diagnose because the symptoms can be similar to other conditions. Sometimes doctors will try waiting a few hours to see how your symptoms develop in hospital. If your symptoms mean it's very likely you have appendicitis, or if your appendix may have burst, doctors may recommend surgery instead of waiting for more tests. Treatment for appendicitis Appendicitis is usually treated with surgery to remove your appendix (an appendectomy). You do not need your appendix, so it's not harmful to remove it. If you need surgery, it will be done as soon as possible, but you may need to wait a few hours. The operation usually takes about an hour. The main steps of an appendectomy are: You'll be given a general anaesthetic , so you'll be asleep and will not feel any pain. The surgeon makes some small cuts in your abdomen (tummy), and uses a thin tube with a camera to see your appendix ( keyhole surgery ). Sometimes they'll need to make a larger cut in the lower right side of your abdomen (open surgery). The surgeon removes your appendix by cutting where it's joined to your bowel. If your appendix has burst, the area will be cleaned. Your abdomen is closed with stitches, clips or glue. Sometimes it's possible to treat appendicitis with antibiotics rather than surgery. This may be recommended if the infection has not spread and surgery is high risk for you. Sometimes appendicitis causes a lump where part of your abdomen and bowel stick to your appendix, called an appendix mass. If this happens you'll usually need antibiotics first, and then surgery a few weeks later if you still have symptoms. Information: Find out more about hospital treatment Going into hospital Having an operation (surgery) Recovering from appendicitis Most people recover from appendicitis in 1 to 2 weeks. It may take longer if you had complications such as a burst appendix. After surgery for appendicitis: you'll have some small wounds in your abdomen (tummy) you'll usually have stitches that dissolve so they do not need to be removed you may have some pain in your abdomen and around your wounds you may have constipation or diarrhoea for several days Recovering in hospital After surgery for appendicitis, you'll spend some time in the recovery room, before moving to a ward. You'll be given medicine to help with pain. How long you'll stay in hospital can vary. If you had keyhole surgery you may be able to go home the day after the operation. If you had open surgery, or any complications, you may need to stay in hospital for a few days. You can go home when doctors think you're well enough. They'll usually want to check that you're eating and drinking, and you're able to poo. You might be offered a follow-up appointment at the hospital or with a GP, but this is not always needed. Recovering at home There are things you can do to help your recovery. Do start going back to your usual activities when you feel ready – you may need to take 1 to 2 weeks off work or school, or sometimes longer depending on the type of work you do take painkillers if you need them follow advice you're given about caring for your wounds while they heal be careful when washing or showering, and replace your dressings if they get wet if you have constipation , eat plenty of fibre and drink lots of fluids – you could also take a mild laxative (ask a pharmacist for advice) if you're given antibiotics , make sure you finish the whole course of treatment contact the hospital ward where you had your treatment, or speak to a GP or practice nurse, if you need any advice about your recovery Don’t do not do strenuous activities such as sport until you've fully recovered – ask your doctor for advice do not drive until you can use a car safely and comfortably, including doing an emergency stop Possible complications of surgery for appendicitis There's a chance of complications during or after surgery to remove your appendix (an appendectomy), but these are rare. Your doctor will explain the risks to you before the operation. Complications can include: the wound becoming infected bleeding scar tissue forming (adhesions), which can cause a blockage in your bowel in rare cases an abscess forming where your appendix was removed appendicitis coming back in the small part of your appendix that was not removed (stump appendicitis) Urgent advice: Ask for an urgent GP appointment or get help from NHS 111 if: You've recently had an appendectomy and you have: soreness or redness around your wound that's getting worse (redness may be less obvious on brown or black skin) bleeding or pus from your wound a high temperature These could be signs of an infection. You can call 111 or get help from 111 online . Risks of a burst appendix A burst appendix (also called a perforated or ruptured appendix) is a serious condition that can lead to complications such as: an infection of the inner lining of your abdomen ( peritonitis ) a life-threatening reaction to infection ( sepsis ) a painful build-up of pus (abscess) a blockage in your bowel problems in pregnancy These complications will need to be treated urgently with surgery and antibiotics. Causes of appendicitis The appendix is a small pouch that's joined to your bowel in the lower right side of your abdomen (tummy). Appendicitis happens when your appendix becomes infected and swollen. This is often caused by something getting stuck in your appendix, such as a small piece of undigested food or hard poo. Appendicitis is common. It can happen at any age, but it's most common in children over 10 years old and young adults. It's rare in babies under 12 months old. Video: what is appendicitis? Watch this animation to learn about what causes appendicitis and how it's treated. Media last reviewed: 1 May 2024 Media review due: 1 May 2027 Page last reviewed: 09 August 2024 Next review due: 09 August 2027</text><label>0</label></item></dataset>